<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Foure sermons whereof two, preached at two assizes, this present yeare, 1638. at Maidestone in Kent, the other two, in his own charge. By Robert Abbot ...</title>
            <author>Abbot, Robert, 1588?-1662?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 173 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 97 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19372</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 58</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100378</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836220</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836220</idno>
            <idno type="VID">478</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19372)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 478)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 905:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Foure sermons whereof two, preached at two assizes, this present yeare, 1638. at Maidestone in Kent, the other two, in his own charge. By Robert Abbot ...</title>
                  <author>Abbot, Robert, 1588?-1662?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 96, 64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Paine, for P. Stephens, and C Meredith, and are to be sold at their shop, at the signe of the Golden Lyon, in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1639.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The SR record is for 5 sermons; the 5th is 59.5, which, although its collation fills a gap in 58, is not found included in any of the copies except C5 and was app[arently]. issued separately by the publishers' change of plan"--STC.</note>
                  <note>"The Christians thrift in keeping: or two sermons preached on 1 Tim.i.19" has separate pagination and caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:478:1"/>
            <p>FOVRE SERMONS, WHEREOF TWO, PREACHED AT TWO ASSIZES, this preſent yeare, 1638, at MAIDESTONE in KENT, the other two, in his own charge.</p>
            <p>By ROBERT ABBOT, Vicar of <hi>Cranbrooke</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Titles</hi> and <hi>Texts</hi> follow on the next <hi>leafe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Paine,</hi> for <hi>P. Stephens,</hi> and <hi>C Meredith,</hi> and are to be ſold at their Shop, at the ſigne of the <hi>Golden Lyon,</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1639.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:478:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:478:2"/>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>THE LORDS ASSIZE, 1 The Text <hi>Iudg.</hi> 11. 27.</label> The Lord the Iudge, bee Iudge this day, betwixt the children of Iſrael, and the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Ammon</item>
               <item>
                  <label>NATVRES ASSIZE, 2 The Text. <hi>Math.</hi> 7. 12.</label> Therefore all things whatſoever yee would that men ſhould doe to you, doe yee even ſo to them, for this is the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>THE CHRISTIANS THRIFT in KEEPING, 34 The Text, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 19.</label> Holding faith, and a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:478:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:478:3"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>REND FATHER IN GOD, AND RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE, WALTER LORD BISHOP of WINTON, High ALMONER to the KINGS moſt excellent Majeſty, &amp; PRELATE of the GARTER, honor in Both lives.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Reverend, and right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; many men are willing to caſt in ſome <hi>of their ſuperfluity</hi> into the Lords treaſurie, the poore widow was willing <hi>to caſt in
<pb facs="tcp:478:4"/> all,</hi> yet little. It is a wonder that ſhee ſhould bee commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded above all thoſe that had fuller hands. But when <hi>Chriſt</hi> lookes to the giver, <hi>a poore widow,</hi> and not to the gift, <hi>two mites;</hi> to the plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in the heart, not to the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nurie in the hand, the wonder ceaſeth.</p>
            <p>My preſent gift is like the widowes, <hi>from my poverty;</hi> yet ſhould I bee an unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full liar if I ſhould ſay, <hi>it is all I have.</hi> God hath vouchſafed mee a double calling: <hi>from himſelf,</hi> inſuch gifts as have made mee willing according to my abilities; and <hi>from the bleſſed church</hi> (wherein I humbly thanke God, to bee borne, brought up, and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve) in ſuch power to exerciſe the
<pb facs="tcp:478:4"/> miniſterie which I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, by <hi>reading, doctrine, approbation,</hi> and <hi>impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whatſoever I have by both, I heartily deſire may bee for <hi>Gods</hi> uſes, and the ſervice of the <hi>Church of God</hi> amongſt us. I cannot commend them as they are acted by mee, it is by a weake body, and a weaker ſoule. As Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> complayned of old, <hi>heimihi! quam contrarius ſum ego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met mihi; ego in ſpiritu, et ego in carne:</hi> ſo more iuſtly may I. I have a long time beene trayned under fightings within, and without and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and anon, am ready to bee over-powered with ſinne, or greife. But as the ramme in fight drawes backe, not to
<pb facs="tcp:478:5"/> quit the field, but to gaine a courſe, to give the greater bruiſe at the next ſhocke: ſo doe I deſire to bee in my infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities. I ſeeme ſometimes to my ſelfe to faint, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to faile, and to beare about mee a dying ſpirit e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day. <hi>Quocunque o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culos converto, video docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta meae aetatis,</hi> ſaid <hi>Seneca</hi> of old, and ſo ſay I.</p>
            <p>Yet looking to what I have received, <hi>ſome ſtrength yet,</hi> to worke, and a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> to keepe mee within my traces, I preſſe hard fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and finde that I looſe not too much ground, <hi>tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough him in whom I am able to doe what I doe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:478:5"/>
            <p>This holds mee up in my worke, and keepes mee in canonicall obedience to my calling, that I may ſay at laſt with bleſſed <hi>Auguſtine, liberavi animam meam,</hi> yea, and ſometimes alſo (though more to ſatisfie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers then my ſelfe) <hi>ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bimus indocti, doctique,</hi> I ſtaine paper with my pen.</p>
            <p>How unable am I for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great taske, no man knowes better then your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, who from my youth have beene a ſtay to my waies, an helpe to my ſtudies, and a comfort to my age, ſince by your Honours ſelfe I have beene accounted worthy to bee your Honours ſervant. But ſince I have not had a reſolved face to deny my poore glea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings
<pb facs="tcp:478:6"/> after the harveſt, to bee brought forth to this learned light wherein we live, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly pray that they may firſt riſe or fall, by your honours cenſure.</p>
            <p>This firſt preſents it ſelfe, my labour that <hi>God may judge, in the judgements of men.</hi> Next to that, my deſire that <hi>Nature bee not ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in her good law, when wee practiſe that wee call juſtice.</hi> And if any thing elſe followes helpe <hi>faith,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in our whole courſe, both publicke and private, whoſoever have beene my friends, from whoſe motions theſe thoughts have beene drawne out, your Honour ſhall bee my firſt judge heere, and patron (if your Honour pleaſe,
<pb facs="tcp:478:6"/> and neede require) to that which is with humbleneſſe confeſt to be unworthy of you. I need not plead reaſons, I am your Honours for humble ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: it is a juſt debt from mee; and that due to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour now, and while I am. Due for your undeſerved fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to my ſelfe. Due for your incouragement to my el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſon while hee was at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</hi> Due for your exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition to my youngeſt ſonne now hee is in <hi>Cambridge.</hi> And if this could bee a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall regiſter of your Honours love and bountie to mee, and mine, I ſhould heartily rejoice. But becauſe mothes and time will eate this out, I ſhall hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deſire to lay up a ſtocke of prayers, for your Honour, in
<pb facs="tcp:478:7"/> heaven. This is all that I can doe, and this is all from mee that your Honour deſires. Would I doe more, I could not, could I doe leſſe, I would not. This I (by Gods Grace) can, and will; and ſo continue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours humble ſervant to be commanded. ROBERT ABBOT.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:478:7"/>
            <head>TO THE TRVELY RELIGIOVS, HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE, NOBLE, AND Worſhipfull Juſtices, and other Gentry of <hi>Kent,</hi> who have heard, and may happen to reade theſe poore Sermons, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to thoſe of his owne Pariſh, all good.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>ONORABLE, Noble, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull, you may juſtly aske, whence this ſight comes? I muſt excuſe it a great deale, <hi>from im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity.</hi> But what is
<pb facs="tcp:478:8"/> the preſent? <hi>A cup of cold water</hi> to good Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Chriſt: and you know that brave commander who did accept of as low a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, from as poore a man as my ſelfe. It will bee rejected; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is too much of that already: Charity and Iuſtice are too much watered, they are growne <hi>cold,</hi> they have waded ſo long that they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nummed, and leſſe apt for uſe. I hope better
<pb facs="tcp:478:8"/> things. They may bee dwarfed in ſome, like thoſe three bones in the head of a man which Anatomiſts call <hi>Malle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olus, Incus,</hi> and <hi>Stapes,</hi> which are as bigge in a child as in a man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but the leſſe the body is in this (I hope) the more is the heate, the more vigorous the ſpirits: &amp; it may be this may wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by an Antiperiſtaſis may make this heate greater, but cannot leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen it in thoſe that are ſo full of goodneſſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:478:9"/>
            <p>Your worths are wel knowne to others, and are beleveed by me: go on ſtill to doe worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>Ephrata,</hi> and to be famous in <hi>Bethlehem.</hi> Doe worthily in piety, do worthily in private charity; and doe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily in publick Iuſtice. Wee have an age made up of too much ſinne, prophane ſwearing, and brutiſh profaning of the Lords day, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, and malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous quarrellings cover too much chriſtians
<pb facs="tcp:478:9"/> ground amongſt us. As it is with the ſea, <hi>there goes that Leviathan, and creeping things innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable;</hi> ſo is it with the land; there are too many maſter ſinnes, and untellable other ſinnes, which wound ſingle, but oppreſſe by heapes. A King wee have by Gods bleſsing never better; lawes ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wiſer, and proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons never more wary: but to make all right, as the oratour magnified <hi>pronunciation,</hi> ſo doe I <hi>execution.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:478:10"/>
            <p>Many hands make light worke: and your hearts will ſet them on worke; <hi>up and be doing.</hi> I neede not provoke your willing mindes: yet may I ſhew you what you do, or ſhould, though I preſſe you not to what you doe not.</p>
            <p>A poore oppreſſed<note place="margin">Surius in vita S. Baſil.</note> woman did obſerve Saint <hi>Baſil</hi> to have ſome credit with the governour of his place. Shee ſolicits him to write to the govenour in her behalfe. The
<pb facs="tcp:478:10"/> good Biſhop preſently tooke pen, inke, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; and wrote to this effect. <hi>This poore woman came unto me ſaying, that my letters have great weight with thee: If it be ſo, heare her, and ſhew it.</hi> The woman carried it, the governour read it, and writes backe this againe. <hi>Holy father; for thy ſake I would have had pitty upon this poore woman, but I could not, except ſhee pay all that is required of her.</hi> The good Biſhop writes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine
<pb facs="tcp:478:11"/> (once more) thus. <hi>Seeing thy will is ready but thy power is wanting, it is a tolerable excuſe: but if thou couldeſt, and wouldeſt not, Chriſt will make thee ſo poore, that where thou wouldeſt, thou ſhalt not be able.</hi> Theſe words were propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call to this unjuſt gover<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour: for not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he fell into the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours diſpleaſure, was caſt into priſon, and expected puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But then he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred Saint <hi>Baſil,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:478:11"/> whoſe interceſsion he ſought, and obtained, and by that meanes, his liberty. Hee then came to Saint <hi>Baſil,</hi> called to minde the poore woman, ſent for her, and reſtored to her the goods, hee wrongfully withheld, <hi>twofold.</hi> Hee would not hazard a ſecond puniſhment for an act of Injuſtice unrepented of.</p>
            <p>My obſervations upon this ſtory are theſe; It is a great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb facs="tcp:478:12"/> to be in authority, it makes the Saints of God on earth to ſue un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. It is a miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable place to bee up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth, oppreſsions may bee done to Gods poore ſervants. It is a fearefull thing not to relieve the oppreſſed when it is in our pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; it caſts the mighty from the throne, and brings them to ſhame. It is a brave thing to doe Iuſtice at firſt: but better late then never, better of love
<pb facs="tcp:478:12"/> then when it is whipt outwith ſtrokes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It is glorious too, not to refuſe to doe right at laſt, when at firſt wee have done wrong as hee: for not one of a thouſand meets with ſuch a day.</p>
            <p>You will bee plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ever to bee better preſidents of Iuſtice then that Iuſticer, and not to ſtand in neede of his beſt part, his late repentance, whereof you are not ſure. And thus, <hi>the
<pb facs="tcp:478:13"/> eyes of the Lord will bee upon the juſt, and his eares will bee open to their prayers: His eyes will bee upon the iuſt.</hi> As hee that hath made a goodly picture, looks upon it againe and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, that hee may ſupply to every defect at laſt: ſo God deales with the godly that are juſt. <hi>His eares are open to their prayers.</hi> When they call he will heare, when they cry, he will ſay <hi>Ecce ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum,</hi> behold here am I,
<pb facs="tcp:478:13"/> nor behold I wil come becauſe hee is hard at hand to comfort them with bleſsings, who comfort others with upright Iuſtice.</p>
            <p>I cannot teach the meaneſt amongſt you in your way: onely I have preſumed to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent this ſtory, and withall to offer to your eyes (if you pleaſe) what you have heard with your eares, <hi>The Aſsize of God,</hi> and <hi>The Aſsize of Nature.</hi> If theſe may ſtand you in
<pb facs="tcp:478:14"/> the leaſt ſtead to ſhew you what you are and doe, and put you in minde what you muſt continue, it is all the hearty wiſhes, &amp; hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble prayers (upon this occaſion) of him that is, and will be</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worthineſſes to uſe in poſsible ſervices ROBERT ABBOT.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:478:14"/>
            <list>
               <head>THE CONTENTS OF THESE SERMONS in ſhort. 1 <hi>The Lords Aſſize, from Iudg.</hi> 11. 27.</head>
               <item>1 <hi>Which is fitted to the time, or ſetting down a triall of</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>The life.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>The liberty</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 <hi>The goods.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4 <hi>The goodname.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of Iſrael<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of Amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>And propounded to perſwade all trials by the Lord the Iudge. Where both.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>What keepes the Lord from judging.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 <hi>When truth is witheld in unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 <hi>By deniall.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 <hi>By falſe accuſation.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>3 <hi>By profit.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>4 <hi>By lingring delaies.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>5 <hi>By flattery, feare, hope, &amp;c.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 <hi>Wher (if truth appeare) judgment doe not attend upon it in full glory,</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>What brings the Lord to judging.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 <hi>When ſuch perſons ſit to judge as God would have.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 <hi>When the whole worke is carried for the honour of the God of truth.</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 <hi>By an holy heart.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 <hi>By an holy hand.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>3 <hi>By an holy eie.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>4 <hi>By an holy mouth.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:478:15"/>
               <head>THE CONTENTS OF THE Second SERMON 2 <hi>Natures Aſſize from Math.</hi> 7. 12.</head>
               <item>1 <hi>Where for introduction 2 knots are clea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>What it is inferred upon?</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>How it is the law and the prophets?</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 <hi>Whether in the law there be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e more then one precept?</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 <hi>Whether there bee a connexion of all vertues, where one?</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>Where for tractation:</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Are examined.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 <hi>Lawes of nature.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 <hi>Principles 2 of nature.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Are ſhewed.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 <hi>The praiſes of this law.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 <hi>The power of it.</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <table>
                                       <row>
                                          <cell>1 <hi>Briefe.</hi>
                                          </cell>
                                          <cell rows="2">
                                             <hi>from</hi>
                                          </cell>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                                          </cell>
                                       </row>
                                       <row>
                                          <cell>2 <hi>Plaine.</hi>
                                          </cell>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Nature.</hi>
                                          </cell>
                                       </row>
                                    </table>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <pb facs="tcp:478:15"/>
                     <item>1 <hi>In ſenſe: layed downe</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 <hi>Negatively.</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 <hi>Not what we liſt.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 <hi>Nor what others doe to us.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>3 <hi>Nor what others do to others.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>4 <hi>Nor what themſelves would.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>5 <hi>Nor what we have bin accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>6 <hi>Nor what profit, honour, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure perſwades.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>7 <hi>Nor as the lawes of the land permit.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 <hi>Poſitively, As would others doe to us.</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 <hi>Whence this rule ariſeth?</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 <hi>When ſelfe-love is right cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity?</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>3 <hi>How this rule of juſtice muſt be carried?</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>In application.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>To all.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>To the occaſion.</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 <hi>With 2 meanes to doe it.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 <hi>With 2 motives to further it.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:478:16"/>
               <head>THE CONTENTS OF THE THIRD, and fourth SERMONS. 3 <hi>The Chriſtians Thrift in keeping, from 1 Tim.</hi> 1. 19.</head>
               <item>1 <hi>Where we are taught.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>To keepe faith, where.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 <hi>How we muſt keep it? By holding,</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 <hi>The ground of faith.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 <hi>The object of faith.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>3 <hi>The act of faith.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>4 <hi>The power of faith.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 <hi>Why we muſt keep it?</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 <hi>Faith is our life.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 <hi>Faith is our power of working.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>3 <hi>Faith is our workeman.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>4 <hi>Faith is our beſt light here.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>5 <hi>Faith makes earth heaven.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 <hi>To keep our keeping of it, and to uſe meanes ro keep it.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Where alſo we are taught.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 <hi>To keep a good conſcience: where.</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 <hi>How we muſt keep it? By keeping.</hi>
                                    <list>
                                       <item>1 <hi>The light of conſcience.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>2 <hi>The love of conſcience.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>3 <hi>The worke of conſcience.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>4 <hi>The charge of conſcience.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 <hi>Why we muſt keepe it?</hi>
                                    <list>
                                       <pb facs="tcp:478:16"/>
                                       <item>1 <hi>If it be gone, God wil be againſt us.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>2 <hi>Without it nothing wil do us good.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>3 <hi>Without it nothing can do us hurt.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>4 <hi>It carries with it more then the whole world.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 <hi>To try our keeping of it, and to uſe meanes to keepe it.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:478:17"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:478:17"/>
            <head>THE LORDS ASSIZE, OR A SERMON ON JVDGES 11. 27.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>The Lord the Iudge, bee Iudge this day betwixt the children of Iſrael and the children of Ammon.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable, Right Worſhipfull, and Beloved;</hi> Be pleaſed to heare theſe words out of the Judges, by Gods aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, driven to an iſſue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Judges. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label>
               <note place="margin">Verbum diei in dieſuo.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It may bee, you will ſay, they are not fit: they yeeld not <hi>a word in due ſeaſon:</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:478:18"/> they ſpeake <hi>of the Lord the Iudge,</hi> and theſe here are men.</p>
            <p>It is true; they are men by <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 82. 6. 2 Chron. 19. 6.</note> nature, but they are Gods by Communion of office, (<hi>I have ſaid yee are Gods:</hi>) and their Judgements <hi>are the Iudgements of God, for God,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iehoſaphat.</hi> But you will <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> ſay, this day will bring forth a Judgement by ordinarie Juſtice, not by warre as that is heere.</p>
            <p>This is true too; yet by the <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13. <hi>Diſtantia 1 Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis. 2 Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis.</hi>
               </note> ſword: for <hi>the Magiſtrate beares not the ſword for nonght.</hi> As all ſinners fight againſt God: (for they ſtand at a double diſtance from him; a diſtance of <hi>perfection,</hi> and of <hi>oppoſition:</hi>) therefore God hath a controverſie with his people, &amp; proclaymeth warr. So criminall offenders fight againſt the face of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:478:18"/> the juſt lawes of the kingdom. This is the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, <hi>whether the lawes ſhall be kept or broken?</hi> And as God, in caſe of rebellion, doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide famine, beaſts, peſtilence and the ſword: ſo Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates come againſt ſuch, not with the ſword of the mouth as Preachers, but with the<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Heb. 11. 34.</note> 
               <hi>mouthes of the ſword,</hi> to bee edged by the lawes for cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, or confuſion.</p>
            <p>The greateſt difficulty will be to fit the perſons, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to be tryed and Judged.</p>
            <p>It is confeſſed, that there wil heere be ſome difference. Heere a pretended title of land is that which drawes on the whole quarrell: but this day will bring forth other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies. Heere the proper ſword of warre decides the doubt: but this day drawes the borrowed ſword of peace,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:478:19"/> for peace. Heere <hi>Iſrael</hi> is againſt uncircumciſed <hi>Ammo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites:</hi> but this day will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile chriſtians by profeſſion, not by practiſe, in thoſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular acts they muſt fall in, and for.</p>
            <p>Yet looke more narrowly into the preſent buſineſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Ammon,</hi> and yee ſhall ſee all the cauſes of this day intertwiſted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ammon</hi> charges <hi>Iſrael</hi> with unjuſt poſſeſſion of land held from them to a long ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Iphtah</hi> the now Judge, being loath to fall upon ſuch a deſperate. Phlebotomy as <hi>Ammon</hi> was prepared for, would firſt pleade out, <hi>Iuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dically,</hi> the cauſe, by embaſſies, to cleare the juſtice of his ſword.</p>
            <p>Hee confeſſeth that they have that land in queſtion: and hee pleades a threefold
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:478:19"/> right unto it. The right of a<note place="margin">1 Jus belli juſti.</note> 
               <hi>juſt warre;</hi> it was gotten by the ſword. The right of <hi>Gods gift;</hi> God, whoſe is the earth,<note place="margin">2 Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio Dei.</note> gave it us, and caſt out the old owners as forfeiters. The<note place="margin">3 Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptio.</note> right of <hi>preſcription;</hi> we have had it foure hundred yeares without clayme or charge of wrong.</p>
            <p>But for the ancient poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of it (that he might croſſe <hi>Ammons</hi> charge) he pleadeth two things. Firſt, that it was <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the land of the <hi>Amorites,</hi> who fought againſt them under <hi>Sehon</hi> their then King: and of the <hi>Moabites</hi> who were juſtly ejected by God. But ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> for the <hi>Amorites</hi> (the now plaintifes,) they had none of their land: that was a falſe charge, a picking of an unjuſt quarrell.</p>
            <p>And that this plea was good is manifeſt in the Records of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:478:20"/> the law, thoſe old reports of God himſelfe. God ſaid,<note place="margin">Deut. 2. 29</note> 
               <hi>thou ſhalt not diſtreſſe or med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with the children of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: for I will not give thee their land which I have given</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 2. 37</note> 
               <hi>to the children of Lot.</hi> There is Gods edict, with the reaſon of it. And <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, <hi>to the land of the children of Ammon thou cameſt not, nor unto any place of the river Iabbock, the land now in queſtion.</hi> There is their obedience to Gods charge, which they kept to that day.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Iſraels</hi> caſe is cleare, yet this prevailes not with <hi>Ammon.</hi> Lyes would have dominion over truth: and <hi>Ammon</hi> would fight though the cauſe were cleared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. He joynes iſſue, takes out his <hi>niſi priùs,</hi> appoints the day of Aſſize, and he will have a triall, <hi>for life;</hi> whether
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:478:20"/> 
               <hi>Ammon</hi> or <hi>Iſrael</hi> muſt live: <hi>For liberty,</hi> whether <hi>Ammon</hi> or <hi>Iſrael</hi> muſt bee homagers: <hi>for Goods;</hi> whether <hi>Ammon</hi> or <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhal have the ſpoyle; <hi>for name,</hi> whether <hi>Ammon</hi> or <hi>Iſrael</hi> is of better credit. And thus the text comes up to the whole buſineſſe of the day.</p>
            <p>Now, when all things were thus prepared betwixt guilty, and innocent, plaintife, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant, the wretched <hi>Ammo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> were like priſoners in<note place="margin">Acts 8. Pro. 5. 22. Rom. 11.</note> the <hi>bonds of iniquity, holden in the cords of their ſins, ſhut up in the priſon of unbeliefe,</hi> and could not ſee the Judge ſet to be the avenger of his people. But <hi>Iephtah</hi> was at more liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. He ſees with fuller eye the Glory and preſence of the juſt Judge. Hee (like a man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident in his cauſe) appeales unto him; calles for theſe priſoners, and plaintifes, to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:478:21"/> the barre; prepares for hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, judgement, execution; and becauſe hee would not have the glory of the day himſelfe, but would give it to the Judge of right &amp; wrong: therefore as <hi>Ioab</hi> before <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bah,</hi> when hee was ready to take it, ſent for <hi>David,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Come thou and take it, leaſt the</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.</note> 
               <hi>victory be attributed to me, and the city bee called by my name:</hi> ſo doth <hi>Iphtah</hi> invite God to the day for all honour, <hi>the Lord the Iudge, Iudge betwixt the children of Iſrael and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſtill you may ſay, that <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> they were <hi>Ammonites</hi> that were to be judged there, and of theſe there were none here.</p>
            <p>It is true perſonally, indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidually <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> it is ſo: but for the cauſe, under pretence of land they would have <hi>life, liberty,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:478:21"/> goods,</hi> and <hi>good name</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> at their mercy, for ſpoyle and prey, and ſo there are too many here, and every where.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſrael</hi> had all their <hi>life</hi> in and from the God of mercy; all their <hi>liberty</hi> from the God of freedom; all their <hi>goods and lands</hi> from the God of boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; all <hi>their credit</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne, from Gods protection and cohabitation: yet <hi>Ammon</hi> unjuſtly ſeekes to diſpoſſeſſe them of all theſe. Hee puts them in feare of life, and ſeeks it. Hee preſents death, and purſues it. Hee hunts after their liberty and would have it. Hee deſires their goods, for a rich booty. Hee baſely takes away their good name, as uſurpers not worthy to live: therfore I appeale to the God of <hi>Caeſar</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iphtah:) the Lord the Iudge, bee Iudge, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:478:22"/>
            <p>By this time (I hope) you ſee <hi>Iſraels</hi> and <hi>Ammons</hi> caſe brought to the full worke of an Aſſize, wherein yee have preſented three particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Judge ſet for the trial of guilty, and not guilty, plaintife and defendant, <hi>the Lord the Iudge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The cauſes to bee heard, the <hi>life, liberty, goods, good name</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>Ammon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The perſons betwixt whom, <hi>the children of Iſrael, and the children of Ammon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, what ſhall I ſay? the ſame or ſuch like cauſes are the worke of this day. Let it therefore be all our wiſhes, deſires, prayers, purpoſes, and practiſes, as it was <hi>Iphtahs,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Lord the Iudge may</hi>
               <note place="margin">The iſſue of the Text.</note> 
               <hi>judge them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. If he doe not Judge, hee will Judge the Judgement. Hee onely is <hi>reaſon it ſelfe,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:478:22"/> wiſedome it ſelfe, juſtice it<note place="margin">Summa ratio.</note> ſelfe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If hee judge them, hee is<note place="margin">Gen. 18.</note> 
               <hi>the Iudge of all the world,</hi> whoſe waies are equall and cannot but judge juſtly.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſhall have an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie aſſize for the maintenance of vertue, and puniſhment of vice, which is alwaies the iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue when the Lord the Judge judgeth.</p>
            <p>But what? ſhall we wiſh to decline the judgements of <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> men?</p>
            <p>God forbid: God is the <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 5.</note> onely Saviour; yet the <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of faith ſaveth too.</hi> God onely converts the heart; yet<note place="margin">Luke 1. 16, 17. Iob 33. 23, 24.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn Baptiſt ſhall turne many hearts of the fathers to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and of the diſobedient to the wiſedome of the juſt.</hi> God onely delivers from hell; yet the <hi>Interpreter, one of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, ſhall deliver a ſoule from
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:478:23"/> the pitte.</hi> God <hi>onely forgives</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mic. 7. 18. Ioh. 20.</note> 
               <hi>ſinnes,</hi> out of authority, as the great Judge; yet <hi>whoſe ſinnes ye remit ſhall be remitted.</hi> In a word, God accounts them as authors with him, that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments from him of good. If therefore men judge with God, from God, the Lord the Judge judgeth too. So be it this day, wee decline them not, let them judge and ſpare not. There are two things<note place="margin">2. What keepes the Lord fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> judging. Rom. 1. 18 1 When truth is withhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righreouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> keepe God from judgement ſeates. Firſt, <hi>when truth is withhold in unrighteouſneſſe</hi>: when it is held in priſon that it cannot ſpeake. Thus the Gentiles did in themſelues: when a beame of naturall knowledge was ready to breake out of them, to give them light to ſee more of God then they did, they withheld and ſmothered it, and ſo God judged not in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:478:23"/> them. Thus it may be at the barre.</p>
            <p>Bee pleaſed to conceive it thus. As in a reaſonable man you may ſee an <hi>Aſſizes</hi> ſet: for there is a <hi>Iudge, Conſcience,</hi> which viewes and cenſures all the waies of man. There is a <hi>Iury</hi> of <hi>naturall or revealed principles.</hi> There is a <hi>priſoner</hi> to be tryed, and that is <hi>truth;</hi> Her <hi>caſe</hi> is this, whether ſhee ſhall bee ſet at liberty yea or no, to goe freely, ſpeake free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, rule freely in all our cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
            <p>Truth pleades, I am the<note place="margin">Veritas o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</note> daughter of the great King: his very Image: But when I appeare, I am hated and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and this bringeth this trouble upon me.</p>
            <p>The <hi>jury</hi> of naturall prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples is ſilenced or corrupted by carnall reaſon and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. The judge hearing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:478:24"/> no evidence is ſilent: and as loath to trouble himſelfe, is content to put off enquirie till another time, <hi>as Foelix.</hi> Heereupon the <hi>will</hi> triumphs<note place="margin">Acts 24. 25.</note> over truth <hi>I will doe as I have done:</hi> and all the <hi>affections</hi> put<note place="margin">Ier. 44.</note> in after the <hi>luſts of the fleſh, the luſts of the eyes,</hi> and <hi>the pride of life.</hi> And thus is <hi>Truth</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Iohn 2.</note> impriſoned, and God the Judge judgeth not in man.</p>
            <p>So in places of judicature <hi>truth is</hi> tryed too. There are judges ſet, godly, wiſe, grave, impartial, hating covetouſnes, and perſons out of the cauſe, who are ready to paſſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence according to allegation, and proofe, ſet on with all good conſcience. There are juries of naturall ſubjects and brethren; who ſhould not be like <hi>Diogenes</hi> his man, who was called <hi>Manes, à non ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nendo,</hi> becauſe he ranne away:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:478:24"/> ſo <hi>jury a non jurando,</hi> becauſe they forget the oath of God, and runne away from it: but muſt preſent according to <hi>truth</hi> ſo helpe them God. There is a glorious <hi>Martyr</hi> to be tryed, and that is <hi>Truth;</hi> which would have truth in perſon of Judge, jurer, guilty, innocent plaintife, and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant: and truth in cauſe too; nothing but truth objected, nothing but truth anſwered, that all may cry, great is truth and it prevaileth.</p>
            <p>But now, if on all ſides<note place="margin">Ioh 18. 38</note> there be <hi>Pilates</hi> good motion <hi>what is truth.</hi> But no further ſifting into the nature, and power of it by <hi>witneſſe, oath,</hi> circumſtances: then are at<note place="margin">Si inficia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri ſat eſt ecquis erit nocens?</note> hand, theſe priſons to with hold truth. The firſt is <hi>veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,</hi> I did it not. And if it be enough to deny, who ſhall be guilty?</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:478:25"/>
            <p>The ſecond is <hi>falſe accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
               <note place="margin">Si accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſſe ſat eſt ecquis erit inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens?</note> by thoſe who are <hi>Graeca fide teſtes,</hi> knights of the poſt, and will ſweare any thing for a fee. And if it be enough to accuſe, who ſhall bee inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent?</p>
            <p>The third is <hi>Profit,</hi> in thoſe<note place="margin">Canes ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticos.</note> who will rouſe up <hi>Verres his hounds,</hi> who continually doe<note place="margin">Dare of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fam Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bero.</note> lie in the winde for gaine, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept a man will ſtoppe their mouthes by ſome fatte mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell.</p>
            <p>The fourth is <hi>off-putting to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriae di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationes.</note> 
               <hi>another time,</hi> that is, lingring and coſtly delayes, though the caſe bee never ſo cleare in truth.</p>
            <p>The fift is <hi>malice</hi> and all ill will, which never ſpeakes well, in thoſe that <hi>pant after the earth on the head of the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 2. 7.</note> 
               <hi>poore, and turne aſide the way of the meeke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And laſtly, that which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:478:25"/> helpes on all theſe is, ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flattery, friendflattery, feare, hope, or ſome other by-place for truths oppreſſion: Theſe or the like priſons are in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe, and then truth is clapt up, and kept out of ſight, like ſome malicious mans adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, who is with great care put in priſon before the day of hearing comes, becauſe he feares his cauſe.</p>
            <p>Say I pray: who Judges now? not the God of truth, but the Prince of darkeneſſe, lying, and vanity.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God is kept from<note place="margin">2. When judgement doth not attend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on truth in full glory.</note> judgement ſeates, when (if truth do appeare) judgements doe not attend upon it in full glory. All judgements of men are not good enough to waite upon truth. There is darkeneſſe in them, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but light in truth: Yet if God will ſo honour our
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:478:26"/> judgements, as to put them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that ſervice; whenſoever ſhe appeares we muſt bee glad to follow her: and for truths ſake to doe, and for truths ſake to die; becauſe God is in truth, and the <hi>faithfull witneſſe,</hi> Chriſt is in truth<note place="margin">Apoc. 1.</note> too.</p>
            <p>To conceive it, call to minde that God requires (as you know) a threefold duty of chiefe magiſtrates. Firſt, to<note place="margin">1 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> adviſe, conſult, and take care for common good, as our good King doth. Theſe are <hi>the ſecrets of government:</hi> which<note place="margin">Arcana imperij.</note> if they were diſcovered, the ſtrength and weakeneſſe of a kingdome would ſoone bee diſcovered to all the world: Therefore privates meddle not with theſe things, that laſt is too large for their ſhooe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to provide by<note place="margin">2 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:478:26"/> lawes, edicts, and proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to keepe every man un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them in good order. And thirdly, to give judgement,<note place="margin">3 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> according to his lawes, and ordinances, <hi>for the puniſhment of evill doers, and praiſe of them</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 4.</note> 
               <hi>that doe well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Judges know their duties under them, that is, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to lawes, edicts, orders helped forth by the God of truth, to waite upon truth, and paſſe judgement for it, with an equall <hi>ballance</hi> of cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>a blinde eye</hi> to perſons, and a ſharpe <hi>ſword</hi> of offence, and defence as neede requires. Now, if this bee away, God judgeth not. He is kept from judgements ſeates, becauſe his truth is not honored and his<note place="margin">2 What brings the Lord to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeates.</note> kingdome of truth advanced. Theſe two keepe the Lord the Judge from judging a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men.</p>
            <p>There are two things al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:478:27"/> which bring God to judge. Firſt, when ſuch perſons ſit to judge as God would have. They ſhould be <hi>ſhepheards</hi> to defend and keepe their flocks:<note place="margin">Pſal. 77. 70. Ezek. 28. 12. Gen. 50. 20. 2 Sam. 14. 17.</note> 
               <hi>ſignets</hi> upon Gods right hand, to ſeale no reſcripts and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants but his: <hi>ſaviours,</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and ſave much people: and <hi>Angels,</hi> to guard the good, and inflict puniſhment upon the wicked. God hath made them images of his <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. When ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſit to judge as God would have.</note> in being ſet aloft; of his <hi>wiſedome,</hi> in making and applying lawes; of his <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> in puniſhing malefactors; of his <hi>mercy,</hi> in paſſing by, and pardoning if neede require; and of his <hi>goodnes</hi> in foſtering and cheriſhing his people. Therfore he maketh glorious Emblems of them in the Scriptures: we reade of one, in the image of <hi>an hee Goate</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 8. 5.</note> 
               <hi>with a notable horne betwixt his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:478:27"/> eies.</hi> There is an <hi>horne</hi> for glory and ſtrength to offend and defend. A <hi>notable</hi> one viſible to all his ſubjects that ſtand in neede. An horne <hi>betweene the eyes,</hi> becauſe it is uſed with circumſpection and wiſedome: ſuch muſt bee a Judge. And let it not grieve them, that they are ſet out by a beaſt, when Chriſt himſelfe is called the <hi>Lyon of the tribe of Iudah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We reade of another in the image of a <hi>goodly ſpreading</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 4 19</note> 
               <hi>tree. A beautifull tree,</hi> becauſe of majeſtie. <hi>A ſpreading tree,</hi> becauſe he offers acceſſe to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. <hi>A fruitfull tree,</hi> becauſe of his doing of good. <hi>A ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowing tree,</hi> becauſe of his mercy. And a <hi>tree having branches for birds,</hi> becauſe he extendeth favours to others according to qualities: Such muſt be a Judge.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:478:28"/>
            <p>But above all, wee reade of<note place="margin">1 Kings 10. 18, 19, 20.</note> 
               <hi>Salomons</hi> goodly throne which was thus ſet out. On each ſide were ſixe Lyons, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all the twelve tribes were ſubject unto him, <hi>not Levie excepted.</hi> Two Lyons before the ſtayres, becauſe two tribes, in after-defection, ſhould not depart from his houſe. The aſſent unto it was by ſix ſteps, whereon when the King aſcended (as the <hi>Rabbines ſay</hi>) the cryer proclaymed thus, when hee was upon the firſt, <hi>wreſt not judgement;</hi> when he was upon the ſecond, <hi>accept no mans per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;</hi> when hee was upon the third, <hi>take no bribe;</hi> when hee was upon the fourth, <hi>plant no groves</hi> for Idols; when hee was upon the fift, <hi>erect no pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> to honour them; and when he was upon the ſixt, <hi>kill not an oxe,</hi> to ſacrifice unto
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:478:28"/> them. And all this to put him in minde of religion and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. If they be ſuch as God hath thus reſembled, this brings the Lord to judge: now, <hi>Gods are come downe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 14. 11.</note> 
               <hi>us in the likeneſſe of men.</hi> Not as if God did not judge though the perſons are faulty: for if ſentence paſſe according to Gods truth, though it bee by <hi>Antiochus, a wicked perſon; Herod, that Foxe;</hi> or <hi>Ananias, that painted wall;</hi> yet theſe ſit in <hi>Moſes Chaire,</hi> heare them: But when their perſons, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, and judgements center and meete in holineſſe, then then are they the fuller image of the Lord the Judge; and hee bowes the heavens and<note place="margin">2 When the whole worke is carried for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the God of truth.</note> comes downe among them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this alſo brings the Lord to judge, when the whole worke is carried for the honour of the God of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:478:29"/> truth. When truth in wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, Oathes, Allegations, Evidences, Judgements, and Records meete, then Chriſts kingdome is advanced, and God is Judge indeede. For here is a conformity betwixt truth and the things that are to honour God.</p>
            <p>If now you ſhall aske mee, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> how this may be? I anſwer; By an <hi>holy heart, hand, eye,</hi> and <hi>mouth,</hi> in the whole worke of the Aſſize.</p>
            <p>There muſt be <hi>an holy heart,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label>
               <note place="margin">By an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heart. Iohn 6.</note> when all perſons are <hi>faithfull</hi> to the rruth. <hi>Chriſt</hi> diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted bread, and fiſh by the hands of his Diſciples to the hungry people: they kept none for themſelves, but gave for Chriſt, and gathered for Chriſt. Here was faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <hi>Ioſua</hi> divided the land of promiſe to the <hi>Iſraelites:</hi> and as if hee had forgot him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:478:29"/> hee reſerved not a part, nor would have any to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his office. Here was faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe too. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> might have amaſſed up a world of wealth to himſelfe in the time of famine; but hee was content with the portion from the King: and here was faithfulneſſe alſo. When all you ſhall receive from the Lord, the King, and the law, &amp; diſtribute faithfully, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſeeking your ſelves, this is an holy heart, <hi>God judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There muſt bee <hi>holy hands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 By holy hands. Hoſ. 4. 18. Gen. 14. 21.</note> when all perſons are not guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>of ſhamefull Give, Give.</hi> Higher powers will hate it: but may they not bee abuſed by ſome inferiours who love it too well? The King of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> when hee was reſcued, ſaid to valiant <hi>Abraham, give me the ſoules<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> take the goods to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:478:30"/> thy ſelfe:</hi> but juſt <hi>Abraham</hi> would have none <hi>from a thread to a ſhooe latchet,</hi> leaſt he ſhould ſay, he had made <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> rich: Here were holy hands. Ye know how it was with <hi>Balaam,</hi> hee would for a reward have <hi>ſaid good of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, and evill of good,</hi> in cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing<note place="margin">Numb. 22. Eſa 5.</note> 
               <hi>Iſrael.</hi> An Angel meets him, his Aſſe ſpeakes, and <hi>Balaam</hi> wonders not, but ſpeakes to his Aſſe againe, <hi>thou haſt mocked mee.</hi> Saint<note place="margin">Auguſt. lib. quaeſt. V.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> wonders at that, and layes the fault upon the love of money, which blockt him up ſo, as he could not ſee miracles to keepe him in a right courſe: his were not holy hands. Take heede: let <hi>Iſrael</hi> be <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>Balaam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There muſt <hi>bee holy eyes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3 By holy eyes.</note> which may be two waies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> firſt, when all are looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:478:30"/> 
               <hi>without any reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</hi> The Judge and the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar are all one (ſaid an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of old,) all appeale unto<note place="margin">1 King. 1. 50. &amp; 2. 29.</note> them. As <hi>Adonijah</hi> runnes to the hornes of the Altar; ſo <hi>Abſalom</hi> in his caſe, referres himſelfe to the King the Judge. Therefore <hi>Cleon</hi> of old, when hee was delegated to the helme of the common wealth, called al his old frinds into a chamber to him, to diſſolve all relations and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects of old frindſhip, that he might looke upon all with impartiall eies. And the old<note place="margin">Ephe. 25. <hi>Bona eſt erga pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perem mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia ſed non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium.</hi> Iob 31. Gen. 12. Gen. 18.</note> Judges of <hi>Athens</hi> called <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagitae</hi> did heare all cauſes in darkeneſſe, where they could ſee no perſons: why ſhould it not be thus ſtill? eſpecially conſidering Gods ſaying, thou ſhalt not reſpect a poore man in judgement. Surely <hi>mercy to a poore man is good</hi> (ſaith
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:478:31"/> Saint <hi>Auguſtine) but not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst judgement:</hi> this is an holy eye.</p>
            <p>Secondly, when <hi>the cauſe is ſearched out diligently.</hi> As God, in the caſe of <hi>Babel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>builders,</hi> and <hi>Sodomites</hi> came down to ſee whether the caſe were according to the cry: ſo muſt all doe that looke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards judgement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>Macedonian,</hi> ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in jvdgement upon one <hi>Machetes,</hi> was not attentive: <hi>he was more ready to ſleepe</hi> then<note place="margin">Dormita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundas.</note> heare (ſaith the Hiſtorian:) yet at the end of the pleading hee pronounced ſentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. Poore <hi>Machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> cryed out, <hi>I appeale.</hi> To whom ſaith <hi>Philip? A te, ad te:</hi> from thee halfe aſleepe, to thee whole awake: with that <hi>Philip</hi> rowzed himſelfe up and heard the cauſe againe. And though hee would not
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:478:31"/> reverſe the ſentence, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credit his publike judgement, <hi>yet hee himſelfe paid the fine to puniſh his owne ſloath.</hi> Heere is an image of an holy eye.<note place="margin">4 By an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mouth.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, there muſt bee an holy mouth, when nothing is ſpoken in judgement which doth not become an holy mouth. Chriſt looketh up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelfe, as the Judge of the world, and ſaith, <hi>I can</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 5. 30. <hi>Non per infirmita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſed per integrita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endi, ſed per obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantiam Iudicandi. Examinat cauſae me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rita, non mutat. Ambroſi.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>doe nothing of my ſelfe:</hi> what nothing? he ſaith not ſo for weakeneſſe, but for integrity; not for his impoſſibility of doing, but for his uprightnes in judging. And againe, <hi>As I heare, I judge:</hi> not judging by pleaſure, but by the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of right judgement. He is not indulgent to his owne will, but doth examine the deſerts of cauſes, and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines without alteration. Heere is an holy mouth. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:478:32"/> wicked men had taken a wicked woman in adultery even in the very act. Chriſt came not to judge as an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly governour; and therefore hee pronounced not ſentence according to the law. Hee doth meaſure them all as wicked perſons, and ſaith, <hi>he that is guiltleſſe throw the firſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 8. <hi>Put a vit lapidanda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſed non a lapidan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis. Ambroſ.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſtone.</hi> Hee though her wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to bee ſtoned, but not by them that would have done it: they muſt pull the beame out of their owne eye, before they undertake that in their brothers: Here againe is an holy mouth. Againe <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> was not invited to<note place="margin">Luk. 7.</note> the Phariſes houſe, but yet ſhee came, and preſſed upon Chriſt; while others intertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him with meate, ſhe did it with teares. Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands her not to be ſhut out of dores though ſhee troubled him at
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:478:32"/> dinner: no hee commandes<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Omnium horarum judex.</hi> Iohn 3. Iohn 4.</note> the grumblers <hi>to let her alone.</hi> He is for all houres, for <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codemus</hi> that came to him by night; and for her that inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts him at meate. It was meate and drinke to him to doe his fathers will: Heere was an holy mouth. Yet once more, <hi>Publius Rutilius</hi> the Roman, when a deare friend preſt him hard with an unjuſt ſuite, denied him. His angry friend cryes out, <hi>what neede I thy friendſhip, if thou wilt not grant mee my requeſt?</hi> He ſhould have beene a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian that thus anſwered, <hi>what neede I thy friendſhip if thou preſſe mee to ſinne againſt lawe and juſtice?</hi> Here is an holy mouth.</p>
            <p>Right honorable, Right worſhipfull, and beloved, oh<note place="margin">Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> that all that are to deale in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny paſſage of juſtice this day
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:478:33"/> were thus good! as that they had ſuch <hi>hearts, hands, eyes,</hi> &amp; <hi>mouthes!</hi> then ſhould the Lord the Judge, judge in the judgements of men.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe that juſtice (as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very other vertue) is harder in practiſe, then in contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, for not onely the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norites<note place="margin">Hiſt. of Councel of Trent.</note> but the <hi>Majorites</hi> are the objects of reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: high as well as low are two guilty; and an oxe flayes hardeſt when he comes to the head. Beſides our vices<note place="margin">Vitia ſunt a dulta &amp; praevalida</note> are not infants, they are growne men and ſtrong: and as <hi>Livy</hi> of old complained of<note place="margin">Neque vitia ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia ferre poſſumus.</note> 
               <hi>Rome,</hi> wee neither can indure faults nor their corrections: ſo may we ſay of ſome popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and Epidemicall vices and ſickneſſes of the ſoule now. This made <hi>David</hi> groane un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the burthen of <hi>Ioab,</hi> who had ſlaine <hi>Abner</hi> a prince, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:478:33"/> a great man in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when he could not doe as he would for the preſent, <hi>I am this day</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam 3. 38. 39.</note> 
               <hi>weake though a King, and the ſonnes of Zervjah are too hard</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 14. 18. <hi>In bonum vniverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>for me:</hi> yet if every one in his place doe <hi>what he could, for the common good,</hi> upon ſound ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining of witneſſes with all circumſtances (which is that which doth bring the edge of the law upon offenders,) then the Lord the Judge judgeth.</p>
            <p>But if it fall out that reaſon<note place="margin">Iudicium legis eſt Iudicium ſolius ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis: Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicium ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis eſt Judicium rationis &amp; libidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</note> ſoundly regulated rule not, (for the judgement of law is the judgement of pure reaſon, the judgement of the man is the judgement of reaſon and luſt:) or if witneſſe bee not truely weighed (as in <hi>Pilates</hi> caſe, who ſentenced Chriſt to death though he might legal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know he was innocent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe<note place="margin">Mar. 14. 59.</note> the <hi>witneſſes agreed not:</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:478:34"/> or if circumſtances bee not<note place="margin">2 Sam. 1.</note> well ſifted, as <hi>David</hi> did, who juſtly put the <hi>Amalekite</hi> to death upon his owne confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that hee killed <hi>Saul;</hi> (for though <hi>Saul</hi> killed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as at leaſt after knowne) yet conſidering theſe two cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances: firſt, that his confeſſion was not out of Phrenſie and diſcontent with his life, but out of full reaſon to claw <hi>David:</hi> and ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that <hi>his bad thoughts</hi> were diſcovered by himſelf <hi>againſt the Lords annoynted,</hi> which juſtly make him an unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy traytor;) his death was juſtly inflicted by <hi>David:</hi>) or if it fall out that conſcience be not fully ſatisfied with the light of truth before verdict, and judgement, and ſo procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings be precipitate and haſty (which <hi>Nero</hi> himſelfe could ſcarce endure, in his firſt part,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:478:34"/> and therefore being mooved to ſet to his hand to an execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he would ſay, <hi>I would I</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vtinam neſcirem literas.</note> 
               <hi>cauld neither reade nor write.</hi>) If either of theſe foure fall out, then the Lord the Judge judgeth not.</p>
            <p>Now (I beſeech you) you having heard thus much; both how you may drive God from, &amp; draw God unto judgement ſeates, preach the reſt of this judge to your own hearts, that ye doe not this day wilfully ſinne againſt his judgement; and ſo I turne to the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the children of <hi>Ammon</hi> and their cauſe.</p>
            <p>The children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> are<note place="margin">2. 3. The par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and their cauſe</note> here in full colours: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like <hi>Adam</hi> in innocency making all the beaſts before them to tremble. They have<note place="margin">1 The chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </note> all the advantage of lawes, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, Judges of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:478:35"/> the Lord the Judge looking upon their caſes.</p>
            <p>You are not <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording<note place="margin">Though wronged.</note> to the fleſh, yet God prevailed with for abundance of bleſſings upon you. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſome of you have been <hi>feared in your lives:</hi> ſome of you have beene <hi>ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in your goods:</hi> ſome of you have beene <hi>hurt in your names:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Muſt get the Lord to judge.</note> ſome of you have beene <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted in your poſſeſſions:</hi> ſome of you have beene <hi>bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in your members:</hi> and in this onely different from the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> heere: As you have the Lord the Judge let the Lord the Judge judge for you in the judgements of men.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Hezekiah</hi> received a blaſphemous letter from<note place="margin">By decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge. 2 King. 19. 14.</note> proud <hi>Senacherib,</hi> hee went to the temple, and <hi>ſpread it before the Lord:</hi> hee thus appealed
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:478:35"/> to this great Judge: you are now as in the temple, even ſo doe you. Shew God your cauſe with honeſt hearts, and ſeeke, and receive judgements as from him. How gloriouſly will this worke? it will make you proceede, not <hi>in the luſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Non Libi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictae ſed amore ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiae.</note> 
               <hi>of revenge</hi> (which God hates) but <hi>in the love of juſtice</hi> (which God loves,) you have the ſword of juſtice in your hands upon the beſt termes: and in truth, Chriſt ſaith for you, <hi>ſell a garment and buy a</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 22. 39.</note> 
               <hi>ſword.</hi> But heare how an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>worthy</hi> meditated upon that text: <hi>O Lord, why doſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambr. in Lucam.</note> 
               <hi>thou bid me buy a ſword, &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeſt mee to ſtrike with it? Surely it is for juſt defence, not for revenge. Thou hast ſhewed me that I could revenge, but I will not of conſcience to thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</hi> Even ſo doe you: So be it. Love law, love juſtice,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:478:36"/> love peace, love truth, but<note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> 
               <hi>vengeance is mine,</hi> ſaith the Lord the Judge.</p>
            <p>Philoſophers ſay that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is the nobleſt ſenſe (if not for diſcipline) yet, for ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall uſe: becauſe it ſuffers not by contrary objects. It can looke upon blacke and white without an appetite of revenge on either. Why ſhould it not bee thus with Chriſtians who are better enlightened by him who is all eye? If your an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyances bee great, let the Lord the Judge judge by his <hi>Iphtahs,</hi> liefetenants, and deputies: and reſt in that without the picklocks of new vexations.</p>
            <p>But if they be leſſe, cloy no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, ſurfet not the honorable bench. <hi>Is there not a wiſe man amongſt you?</hi> ſhall the pillars<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.</note> of the earth weare themſelves
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:478:36"/> out in bruiſing duſt ſmall, when there are mountaines enough to levell? God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid. If you and your cauſes are ſuch, the Lord the Judge will not judge for you at laſt.</p>
            <p>But for the children of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 The Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Ammon.</hi>
               </note> where are they? It is pitty they have not a ring in ſome place of this crowne, that the word may fall upon them like raine upon the dry ground. They are peeping out of their gates, thinking this time too ſhort, which (haply) ſome of you do think too long. I can ſay nothing to them, becauſe abſent: yet give mee leave to ſpeake a word of them, againſt them, for them. This be ſpoken of<note place="margin">1 Of them.</note> them. They are ſuch as love not the law. Though <hi>let the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vivat Rex, cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. Lex.</note> 
               <hi>King live, and the law runne</hi> be the good ſubjects prayer: yet
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:478:37"/> the old law <hi>Iulia</hi> could not pleaſe adulterers; nor the law <hi>Cornelia,</hi> murtherers; nor the law <hi>Rhemnia,</hi> promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; ſo nor our lawes can pleaſe thoſe wicked <hi>Belialiſts:</hi> Their bliſters muſt bee let out.</p>
            <p>This bee ſpoken againſt<note place="margin">2 Againſt them. <hi>Ne ſint pedes ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mium la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nei, ne tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us fint nimium ferreae.</hi>
               </note> them. They have lived in this bleſſed Church, where they might have beene better taught, or, if they have beene taught, where they have unlearned many a good leſſon. If the miniſtery can doe no good, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate muſt take the care. <hi>Let not your feet bee too much made of wooll, leaſt at laſt your hands bee made of two much yron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Magiſtrates, and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are compared to the teeth. Some are <hi>Cutters,</hi> which cut the meat, and<note place="margin">Inciſores.</note>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:478:37"/> forme the voyce: theſe are like miniſters who convince<note place="margin">Tit. 1 13 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Molares.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>cuttingly.</hi> Some are grinders, which bruiſe the meate and fit it for paſſage: theſe are like magiſtrates who (by ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice) bruiſe the ſonnes of wickedneſſe in peeces, and ſend them downe into the draffe of the world. Neither let it grieve you to be ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, ſeeing Chriſt is called the <hi>Rock of offence,</hi> that breaks them in peeces on whom hee falls.</p>
            <p>This laſtly, bee ſpoken for<note place="margin">3 For them.</note> them. They are ſubjects, (though bad ones;) for elſe the law could not fall on them. And though they have made themſelves of chriſtians in name, <hi>Barbarians</hi> indeede in particular acts: yet are they of two ſorts. Some are <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Errones: Turbones.</note> and ſome are <hi>miſleaders:</hi> ſome are apprentices to ſinne,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:478:38"/> ſome monſters in that blacke art.</p>
            <p>Now doe but conſider how<note place="margin">For mercy of Gods making.</note> carefull the Lord the Judge is, leaſt he ſlay with the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the righteous, who are ſo either in preſent act, or under charitable hope. If he worke a worke of mercy, <hi>hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth in mercy,</hi> if a worke of<note place="margin">Mic. 7. 18.</note> juſtice, hee calleth it <hi>a ſtrange worke,</hi> becauſe <hi>hee ſhaves with</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 26. 21</note> 
               <hi>a razor that is hired,</hi> if he had no juſtice of his owne. If he<note place="margin">Eſa. 7. 20.</note> be to work a worke of juſtice, he is <hi>ſlow to anger,</hi> &amp; comes to<note place="margin">Exod. 34.</note> it <hi>when there is no remedy:</hi> but if a worke of mercy, he <hi>is rich</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Chro. 36. 15.</note> 
               <hi>in mercy, abundant in goodneſſe.</hi> If he looke upon occaſions, it is a great matter that mooves his juſtice: when <hi>the ſinnes of the Amorites are at the full;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 15. 16.</note> when all fleſh had corrupted her waies, and <hi>the wickedneſſe</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 6. 5.</note> 
               <hi>of man was great in the earth;</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:478:38"/> when old and young, even, <hi>all the people from every quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 19. 4</note> were given to ſinne: but a ſmall matter mooves him to ſhew mercy. If there be but <hi>tenne men in Sodom;</hi> If<note place="margin">Gen. 18.</note> there bee but one <hi>Iacob</hi> in the houſe of <hi>Laban,</hi> one <hi>Moſes</hi> praying for <hi>Iſrael,</hi> one <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nehas</hi> executing judgement, and one man in <hi>Ieruſalem</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 5. 1.</note> 
               <hi>that ſeekes the truth,</hi> hee will ſpare multitudes. So doe you, and proſper when it is fit. God is well pleaſed if you follow his owne ſonne, who excuſed his diſciples in ſome infirmities, ſaying, their <hi>ſpirit is willing,</hi> their<note place="margin">Mat. 26. 41. Eph. 5. 9.</note> 
               <hi>fleſh is weake,</hi> and hee is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver angry, if yee <hi>follow him as deare children</hi> in workes of imitable mercy.</p>
            <p>Onely know, this is Gods<note place="margin">Salvis prietate &amp; juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia.</note> rule, that mercy muſt never bee ſhewed, but when <hi>piety</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:478:39"/> and <hi>juſtice</hi> can bee kept ſafe and ſound. Thus doe, and yee ſhall this day be <hi>Ieph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tahs</hi> appealing to the Lord the Judge to judge betwixt the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the children of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that yee may doe thus, the Lord the Judge grant unto you, who lookes upon no man in his perſon, all men in their cauſe: and hath made himſelfe to you a patterne of executing ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and mercy; and that for IESVS CHRIST his ſake, who is the <hi>Lambe</hi> of mount <hi>Sion,</hi> the <hi>Saviour,</hi> the <hi>Lion</hi> of the tribe of <hi>Iudah</hi> the <hi>Iudge,</hi> and is angry with them that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour not the father, kiſſe not the Sonne, and grieve, reſiſt, quench, and deſpiſe the Spirit; to the which
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:478:39"/> coeſſentiall, coeternall, and coequall <hi>Trinity,</hi> bee all kingdome, power, and glory henceforth and for ever</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:478:40"/>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:478:40"/>
            <head>NATURES ASSIZE, OR A SERMON ON MATH. 7. 12.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Therefore all things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever yee would that men ſhould doe to you, doe ye even ſo to them: for this is the law and the Prophets.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable, Right worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and beloved: the laſt time I preſented unto you the <hi>Aſſize of God,</hi> and now I ſhall (if God pleaſe) lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you <hi>the Aſſize of nature,</hi> if both ſhall meete in Gods rule, example, and your imitation, ye can not faile in the work of the day.</p>
            <p>All ſcriptures are good, and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:478:41"/> fit to <hi>make perfect,</hi> yet have<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 17.</note> they an accidentall difference as inſtruments of muſick. Some like <hi>Iacobs haſel rods,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. Mar</note> are partly pilled, and partly covered: ſome, like <hi>Ahabs</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 5.</note> 
               <hi>houſe of Ivory,</hi> are without a covering. Some are like <hi>milke,</hi> ſome like ſtronger meate. Some are ſo cleare that the<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 19. 2 Cor. 3.</note> 
               <hi>day-starre ariſeth</hi> with them in our hearts: and ſome are darke through the <hi>vaile upon</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.</note> 
               <hi>our minds.</hi> As <hi>one ſtarre diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth from another in glory,</hi> yet are all heavenly bodies; ſo is it with the ſcriptures: ſome are large in handling weighty matters, ſame bind up much in a word.</p>
            <p>This heere is of the playner ſort (as all highly neceſſaries are.) So <hi>cleare</hi> that he is blind that ſees it not: ſo <hi>emphaticall</hi> that hee is an adamant that is not mooved: ſo <hi>ſhort</hi> that a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:478:41"/> ſnaile hath more blood, then<note place="margin">Plus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet limax ſanguinis, quam ille ſenſus.</note> hee hath ſenſe that receives not much in a little. Yet muſt you ſuffer a little more then a word of exhortation, to convey unto your ſoules that little which I can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend from them.</p>
            <p>They containe a ſure rule of juſtice: but every word muſt be ſcanned to bring it to the practiſe even of a willing people.</p>
            <p>The very firſt word (<hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi>)<note place="margin">1 There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes.</note> is not without a knot: for it may be asked, <hi>upon what it is inferred?</hi> Some thinke it to referre to the juſtice in the chapters foregoing; but this <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> concluſion would be too farre ſeparated from the premiſes by <hi>the God of order.</hi> Some thinke it to bee redundant, as many elegancies in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are. But certainely it is <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer▪ </seg>
               </label> not in vaine: It is of good
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:478:42"/> uſe, and a note of an excellent concluſion to be for ever held out of it ſelfe. <hi>Nature</hi> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it, <hi>the law</hi> and the <hi>prophets</hi> revive it: <hi>therefore hold it, doe it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt words have a<note place="margin">2 How this is the law and the Prophets.</note> greater knot. For how can this bee ſaid <hi>to bee the law and the prophets,</hi> ſeeing <hi>they</hi> ſet downe the love of God, and the promiſes of ſalvation by Chriſt, as well as Iuſtice to each other?</p>
            <p>Hereupon two queſtions are diſputed in the ſchooles. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label>
               <note place="margin">Whether more then one pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept. Rom. 13. 9</note> Firſt, <hi>whether in the law there be more then one precept yea or no?</hi> The doubt ariſeth thus. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>if there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other commandement, it is briefely comprehended in this, thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelfe:</hi> And Chriſt ſaith heere doe as you would bee done unto: <hi>for this is the law
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:478:42"/> and the prophets:</hi> therefore it ſeemes there is but one. But <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> ſeeing the Apoſtles mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Eph. 2. 15. <hi>Aquin. 1a. 2 ae<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> q. 99. Art. 1.</hi>
               </note> one <hi>law</hi> of many <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements;</hi> it is reſolved thus, that there is but one pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept with the reſpect to the full end, <hi>charity:</hi> but there are more with reference to the meanes ſubſervient to it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, hence it is asked, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label>
               <note place="margin">Whether there be a connexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all vertues. Iam. 2. 10.</note> 
               <hi>whether there be ſuch a connex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion of vertues, that where one is in truth, there are all the reſt?</hi> This doubt ariſeth from two texts too. Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, <hi>whoſoever ſhall keepe the whole law, and yet offend in one point, is guilty of all.</hi> If it bee thus in breach, it is thus in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement. For there is but one body of legall juſtice, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to doe, or ſinne againſt. And Chriſt ſaith here, that to<note place="margin">Io. de corb. com. the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ol. lib. 5. c. 8.</note> doe as we would be done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to is <hi>the law and the prophets.</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:478:43"/> If juſtice to men bee the law and the prophets, then ſurely where that is in truth, all that they require is by way of concatenation, and chayning<note place="margin">Wall. Eth Ariſt. Majores extravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia quàm intravir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes.</note> together. This queſtion is expounded to be underſtood of <hi>perfect</hi> and gratuitous ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, which are by infuſion, not of ſuch as are acquired by induſtry. Of theſe it is ſaid of the grave moraliſts of old, that <hi>they are greater in being without vice, then in being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the liſts of true vertues.</hi> Of thoſe there are ſome that are more noble then others: and therefore are they called <hi>the mothers of vertue.</hi> Thus <hi>Faith</hi> is the mother of vertue in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall;<note place="margin">Matres virtutum. 1 Origine. 2 Educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one.</note> for out of the acts of faith theſe flow: <hi>Charity</hi> in education; for it feedes them all with faiths proviſions: <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility</hi> in conſervation; for they being raked up in her
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:478:43"/> aſhes are kept alive: and <hi>pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi>
               <note place="margin">3 Conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatione. 4 Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine.</note> in government; for it ſhe doe not order them all, they are not carried without a ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh. Though theſe have thus their due glory, yet where one is in truth, there are all the reſt in linke.</p>
            <p>Some ſubtile doctors goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt<note place="margin">Scotiſtae.</note> this being overſwayed (as they thinke enough) by experience. But though of the ſhadowes of vertues this be true: yea, and this bee as true of true vertues, that ſome are more conſpicuous then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by humane aptneſſe, fitneſſe of the inſtrument, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, time, and occaſions: yet <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> it is better reſolved affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively. The ſubject requires <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> it, <hi>a vertuous man,</hi> who can not bee at one time good and bad, happy and unhappy, which yet he could be, if hee had ſome vertues, and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:478:44"/> others. <hi>Gods bounty</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it, which gives not one <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> vertue, <hi>to fit receivers,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the others. The <hi>weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſolitary vertue in it</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>ſelfe</hi> requires it: for as one member needs another, ſo doth one vertue neede her fellowes. And laſtly, <hi>the uſe of vertues</hi> muſt have it ſo too. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> For they are to oppoſe all and ſingular vices: therefore muſt there bee a linking of all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, to oppoſe and repreſſe the chaine of all vices.</p>
            <p>As if there bee but one <hi>ſtring</hi> wanting in an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, there can be no perfect harmony: ſo nor ſpirituall melody in the ſoule if one vertue be abſent. As a <hi>ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier</hi> is not well furniſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an enemie, except hee be in compleat armes: ſo nor the chriſtian ſouldier except hee have the whole vertuous armour of God. As the <hi>ſtarrs,</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:478:44"/> and planets are alwaies in their ſpheares to make a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect firmament: ſo are theſe lights of vertues to make an upright ſoule. And as a <hi>phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke garden,</hi> or <hi>Apothecaries ſhop,</hi> are defective, if any hearb or drugge for uſe be wanting: ſo is it with a ſoule that hath not the whole body of phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke againſt the whole body of ſinne and death.</p>
            <p>Thus therefore wee might conclude from hence: but we neede not goe ſuch a circle to untie Chriſts knot here. For <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quest. </seg>
               </label> if it be asked, <hi>how juſtice to our <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
                  </label> neighbours can bee the law and the prophets?</hi> you muſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Secundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſubjectam materiam.</hi> 1 Cor 9. 22.</note> Chriſt ſpeakes accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the matter in hand. As when <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>to all men I became all things,</hi> he muſt not bee underſtood to comply with the ſtoole of wickednes, but that in matters indifferent, which were neither co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:478:45"/> nor forbidden, hee did ſo. Even ſo Chriſt ſpeakes here of all things concerning cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and juſtice betwixt man and man.</p>
            <p>Wee are thus come from<note place="margin">1 This text is a law of nature.</note> both the ends to the heart and middle of this text, which layes downe a great <hi>law</hi> and <hi>principle</hi> of nature for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing of juſtice among men, <hi>to doe even ſo</hi> to others, as wee would that others ſhould doe to us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is a law,</hi> and there are<note place="margin">3 Sorts of lawes.</note> three ſorts of lawes. The <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall</hi> law in God; which is his counſell and will for the being, ſupportation, and order of the world. By vertue of this we have a creation, and a providence. The <hi>naturall</hi> law in the creature; which (referred to man) is the law of God <hi>written in his heart,</hi> for<note place="margin">Rom. 2. 15.</note> the view of the underſtrnding
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:478:45"/> to informe, and of the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to binde to doe, or to binde over for not doing. Laſtly, the <hi>impoſed</hi> law upon the creature: which is that poſitive law in the ſcriptures, to revive and perfect the law of nature which through tract of time, and cuſtome in ſin was in great part worne out.</p>
            <p>This heere was firſt a law of nature, now poſitively revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: which through the foule ſhooes of ſin though it bee worne into ragges and ſhreads, becauſe <hi>we are made vagabonds from our owne hears</hi>
               <note place="margin">Facti ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus fugi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tivi a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris.</note> (therfore we reade of ancient Germans who did allow of theft, and of our Northerne borderers, who were perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that the eight co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eights putting in:) yet is it of excellent uſe to revive
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:478:46"/> theſe old ſtatutes, as Chriſt doth in this place; that wee may be helped to feele our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, and find our need of the law of Chriſ. Thus it is a law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is a principle of nature too</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 It is a principle of nature alſo. 1 <hi>Primo prima principia.</hi>
               </note> and there are two ſorts of principles which are bound up in the heart of man. <hi>The firſt before others,</hi> which are made up without diſcourſe, and helpe from without. Though theſe be not alwaies in perfect act, yet may they alwaies be knowne, as a ſtone by the weight may be known to move downeward, though it doe not alwayes ſo doe. <hi>The ſecond next unto the firſt,</hi> which<note place="margin">2 Secundo prima priucipia.</note> are made up of the firſt by diſcourſe, as concluſions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in them. As thus, I may not defile my neighbours wife, hurt his goods, life, or the like, becauſe I would not
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:478:46"/> have another deale ſo with mee.</p>
            <p>This here is of the firſt ſort; which if it bee quickened is hard at hand to promote ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. As when you write up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Paper with the juice of an onion (as many ſay) the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters at firſt are not legible, but bring it to the fire and warme it, and then ye may reade it. So at the firſt (in ſome) yee can reade little or nothing of this law: but bring it to the fire of the word and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and all Juſtice to men will appeare to your comfort, or conviction.</p>
            <p>Thus doth our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour here. He knowes that if the flies of <hi>Aegypt</hi> get into our eyes, the frogges of <hi>Aegypt</hi> will ſoone get into the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of our hearts, and then the catterpillers of <hi>Egypt</hi> will deſtroy the fruits of our lives.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:478:47"/> Therefore he rubs and chafes the light of the law upon their, and our conſciences, that it may be better read and done in after times. As if hee ſhould ſay, I am ſure that<note place="margin">Amor 1 concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcentiae. 2 charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</note> ſome of you, by the <hi>love of luſt,</hi> others by the love of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, doe love your ſelves; yee would not be hurt in honour, life honeſtie, juſtice, or truth: therefore <hi>all things whatſoever yee would that others ſhould doe to you, even ſo doe to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To bring the law, and<note place="margin">2 The text opened &amp; applied.</note> principle cloſe up unto you, be pleaſed to receive,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 The prayſes of it,</item>
               <item>2 The power of it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The prayſes of it are theſe:<note place="margin">1 By the prayſes of the law.</note> 
               <hi>that it is Chriſts briefe, yet plain ſumme of all juſtice to men.</hi> To be ſhort for memory, and plaine for underſtanding, doe ſeldome meete in the wordes of men. If wee labour to bee<note place="margin">Dies bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis eſſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boro ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurus fio.</note>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:478:47"/> ſhort, wee are ſo much the more obſcure, But this is ſo ſhort, that the poore man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not complain, <hi>he cannot buy it:</hi> ſo plain that the ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t man cannot complaine, <hi>hee cannot comprehend it,</hi> when it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to him and it is thus ſhort, and plaine from Chriſts mouth (as wel as natures voice), who is the wiſedome of the father<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that one law-gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and Judge of the world, for rewards and puniſhments.</p>
            <p>Therefore certainely it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to all his ſubjects: none can plead immunity from the ſound and tranſcendent equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it, and from the way to bleſſing or curſing according to our dealings with men. For <hi>they will not thaet I rule o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them,</hi> (ſaith the ſame <hi>Chriſt) bring them forth and ſlay them before me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may bee you will ſay: If<note place="margin">Ob.</note>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:478:48"/> 
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> have given me ſo plain a ſum, what neede I ſo much preaching to teach me juſtice to men?</p>
            <p>I anſwer; though it bee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> ſo briefe and plaine, yet preaching is neceſſary for a double uſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to expound, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the particulars: Husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry, is a ploughing, ſowing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> reaping, threſhing; yet there needes teaching an art in all theſe, or the commonwealth would ſtarve: ſo muſt we be taught <hi>an holy art</hi> in our chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian duties. <hi>Secondly,</hi> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade<note place="margin">Heb. 13. 22.</note> the practiſe of it. <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you brethren</hi> (ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) <hi>ſuffer the wordes of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, for I have written un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you in few wordes.</hi> The fewer wordes the neceſſary rule hath, the more words of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation are neceſſary to draw on doing. The <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:478:48"/> is blinde, and may judge amiſſe of plaine things, as <hi>Zebul</hi> ſaid, they may ſee<note place="margin">Iud. 9. 36.</note> the ſhadow of the mountains like men: and as the <hi>blinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 8. 24.</note> under cure ſaid, I ſee men walking like trees: ſo may the <hi>underſtanding</hi> miſgive us. The <hi>will</hi> is perverſe, therfore beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and bands muſt come, the rod, and the ſpirit of meeknes, line upon line, precept upon precept, till <hi>judgement bee brought to victory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet you may urge for <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> your owne quiet, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out more adoe Chriſts words are full of briefe and plaine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; therfore ſay no more. This is true; and I humbly <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> pray that they may prevaile accordingly. Oh that all our lawes were briefe, preſenting the majeſty of a commander, not the art of an expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der!</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:478:49"/>
            <p>It is an old ſaying of a wiſe<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lex jube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, non diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet: Sen.</hi> 1 Cor. 1 4.</note> Stoick, <hi>the law muſt command, not diſpute.</hi> Oh that our laws were plaine! for if <hi>the trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet give an uncertaine ſound,</hi> who will gird himſelfe unto the battaile? The riddles of the old oracles bred many a mans ruine. Oh that all might fall upon all with equity. The law ſhould not bee a mother<note place="margin">Non aliis mater, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is nover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca.</note> to ſome, and a ſtep-dame to others: but (circumſtances conſidered) ſhould look with the ſame eye upon rich and poore. But becauſe, be it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo plain, briefe, and equal, yet it is rather to bee hoped, then found, in all points, as it ſhould: therefore aſcend wee from the praiſe of this law, to the power of it, which will be ſeene,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 In the ſenſe, and</item>
               <item>2 In the application of it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>No man diſaffected to the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:478:49"/> truth is an enemy to the ſenſe of any of Gods oracles. The<note place="margin">The ſenſe of this law.</note> ſenſe of this may be taken up two wayes, firſt, negatively, ſecondly, poſitively.</p>
            <p>Negatively, wee muſt doe<note place="margin">Negative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note> to others, <hi>not what we list.</hi> It is cruelty and tyranny to runne<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sic volo, ſic jubeo.</hi>
               </note> this race, <hi>thus I will, thus I command.</hi> Our wills are cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, &amp; if we follow them, the cart goes before the<note place="margin">Fertur e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis auri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gae.</note> horſe. If a man have power, and imploy it thus, <hi>Salvian</hi> will ſalute him thus, <hi>a rich po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dives po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtas pauperem facit eſſe rempub: sal. de Guber. lib. 2.</note> 
               <hi>not well regulated, makes a poore</hi> Church, <hi>common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,</hi> or family.</p>
            <p>Wee muſt doe to others, <hi>not as others doe to us;</hi> mens actions towards others are ordinarily thus excuſed, <hi>why did he thus to me?</hi> therefore are they at an eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth, even by private revenge. They hold
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:478:50"/> this good charity, <hi>to deceive</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fallere fallentem noneſt fraus.</note> 
               <hi>him that deceives me, is no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit in me.</hi> But as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>we muſt not render evill for evill:</hi> ſo <hi>Xenophon</hi> did when one rayled on him, <hi>thou haſt learned</hi> (ſaid hee) <hi>to ſpeake ill, but I to contemne it, and ſpeake good,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee muſt doe to others, <hi>not as others doe to others.</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples<note place="margin">Exempla haberi poſſunt pro teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monio. Sal. lib. 2.</note> are too often accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted teſtimonies (not onely of things lawfull, but of things neceſſary, though without a law,) that begins preſently to be lawfull, which by patternes is growne publick; men are<note place="margin">Incipit eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe licitum quod ſolet eſse pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licum. Cypri.</note> too apt to looke upon preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents. <hi>Plato's</hi> ſchollars fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed his crookedneſſe; <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle's</hi> ſtammering, and <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anders</hi> courtiers his ſtouping: ſo will men follow others, though to their owne and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wrong. It is ſafe (ſaith
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:478:50"/> the politician) to offend when<note place="margin">Tutum eſt peccare autoribus illis.</note> ſuch, and ſuch, goe before us. But wee muſt live by Gods rules, not by the examples of men, wee muſt doe to others, <hi>not as men themſelves would.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>Saul</hi> would have had his Page kill him, and <hi>Abime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech</hi> would have ſo died, out of pride, that it might not bee ſaid, a woman had overpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erd him. It is ſaid indeed, that <hi>to him that is willing to</hi>
               <note place="margin">volenti non fit injuria.</note> 
               <hi>receiue it, an injury cannot bee done.</hi> But this is not alwayes true, yea ſometimes falſe: therefore <hi>Ioſeph</hi> had learned to run away, when <hi>Potiphars</hi> wife would willingly have had him to her Iuſtful imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: and the friends of the <hi>Demoniack</hi> pulled him out of the fire, and water, though in deviliſh raptures hee would caſt himſelfe into them.</p>
            <p>Wee muſt doe to others, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:478:51"/> 
               <hi>not as wee have accuſtomed to doe;</hi> Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring how it came to paſſe, that our fore-fathers did themſelves, and others, ſo much wrong, as to have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wives, anſwereth, <hi>ſurely</hi>
               <note place="margin">Certè cùm fuit mos, non ſuit eulpa. Amb.</note> 
               <hi>when it was a cuſtome; it was no crime</hi> But cuſtome is no good plea, though in common courſe it ſometimes findes <hi>reaſonable</hi> plea, and paſſage; yet will it hardly bee heard in the court of conſcience, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt equity. For <hi>the cuſtome of ſinne, will blunt the ſenſe of</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do peccan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di tollit ſenſum peccati. Cedat conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti. Text.</hi> 6 Pro 30. 15. <hi>vivitur ex rapto.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſinning,</hi> either againſt our ſelves, or others; therefore let cuſtome vaile the bonnet, and give place to truth.</p>
            <p>Wee muſt doe to others, <hi>not as profit perſwades.</hi> If the horſe-leaches two daughters cry, <hi>give, give,</hi> then are men apt to bee wolves to others, and <hi>to live upon the ſpoile. Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hazi</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:478:51"/> will lye, and deny for gaine: <hi>Achan</hi> will ſteale for<note place="margin">Lingua i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doli, ſic gladius ab antiquis.</note> the golden ſword, and coſtly <hi>cloake</hi> of the <hi>Idoll:</hi> and <hi>Iudas</hi> will betray his maſter, though it be <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe. Thus by the unrighteouſneſſe of ſinne, profit will make men fall into the unrighteouſneſſe of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance. It is an ill rule of juſtice.</p>
            <p>Wee muſt doe to others, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 
               <hi>not as pleaſure allures.</hi> If this prevailes, <hi>Ahab</hi> will be ſicke for <hi>Naboths</hi> vineyard; <hi>Dives</hi> will rowle in pleaſure while <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſtarves at his gate; and <hi>Iſrael</hi> will have the <hi>calves</hi> of the ſtall, wine in bowles, and inſtruments of muſicke like <hi>David,</hi> but withall he wil forget the afflictions of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph.</hi> Pleaſure cannot bee the rule of juſtice: for <hi>I ſaid to laughter thou art mad, and to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 2.</note> 
               <hi>joy, what is that thou doeſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:478:52"/>
            <p>Wee muſt doe to others. <hi>not as honour prickcs us on.</hi> He that affects to riſe from the ground to the ſtirrop, from the ſtirrop to the ſaddle, from the faddle to the throne, from the throne to the triumphant chariot, had neede of a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent law to this, to rule in his carriage to others. Hee will make a path of men to walke upon, horſes of mens ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to ride upon, wine of mens blouds, carouſing cups of their ſculls, and ſacrifices of their perſons to honour him in the way. If <hi>Haman</hi> would have all the honour, all the Jewes muſt dye as well as the offender. If <hi>Abſolom</hi> would judge, his owne father muſt ſuffer. Yea, if but a praiſe (the ſhadow of honour) falls from the mouth of one that ſhould bee puniſhed. In ſuch a caſe, when the Devill praiſed
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:478:52"/> 
               <hi>Chriſt,</hi> hee cried out, <hi>hold thy</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 1. 2 4 3 5. <hi>Laus mea eſt ſilenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um tuum, nolo me laudet vox tud, ſedtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a, poena tua laus mea. Chryſoſt 9</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>peace,</hi> as if hee ſhould ſay, my praiſe is thy ſilence, I will not that thy voice praiſe mee. but thy torments, thy puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall bee my praiſe. But men doe farre otherwiſe: this is a bad rule of juſtice.</p>
            <p>Wee muſt doe to others, <hi>not as the lawes of the land per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit.</hi> Though high honour be to bee given to the lawes of nations (for they are the wall of vertue, and the bridle, and ſcourge of vice) yet muſt wee not abſolutely reſt in them for all juſtice. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they are <hi>permiſſive, not preceptive,</hi> like <hi>Moyſes</hi> bill of divorce for the hardneſſe of mens hearts: ſuch is the law of uſury. Sometimes they are <hi>corroſive commanding;</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided to eate out the dead fleſh of vice, therefore appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable only in ſuch caſes: ſuch
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:478:53"/> is that for taking of forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which is unjuſt, when the cure can bee had without ſuch a remedy. Sometimes they are <hi>for terrour, not for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant obedience;</hi> as when they ſet downe the worſt to keepe unruly ſpirits in better courſe. In ſuch a caſe, extreame right, is extreame wrong. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<note place="margin">Ius Rha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>thae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, et re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocum.</note> the whole law of the kingdome is made up of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and conſciencious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamity, and mitigation, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour and chancery. Therfore not always what law permits, is the rule of juſtice.</p>
            <p>If now wee may not doe to others what we liſt, nor what others doe to us, nor what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers doe to others, nor what others would, nor what wee have uſed, nor what profit perſwades, nor what pleaſure allures, nor what honour prickes us unto, nor what the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:478:53"/> lawes permit, <hi>what then is our rule of juſtice?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Poſitively, we muſt doe to<note place="margin">2 Poſitively.</note> others, <hi>ſo as wee would that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſhould doe to us.</hi> The an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering of two or three que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions will cleare all of this.</p>
            <p>Firſt, whence the rule doth<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> 1. Whence this rule doth ariſe?</note> ariſe? It ariſeth from <hi>ſelfe:</hi> what <hi>yee</hi> would to <hi>you.</hi> This cannot but direct aright: for no man hates <hi>himſelfe,</hi> intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally, but loves and cheriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>himſelfe.</hi> It may bee you <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> will ſay, <hi>the love of our ſelves may be vicious,</hi> and then it is no ſafe rule of our love to others. This is moſt true: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> therefore if the love of God be oppoſed to the love of our ſelves, in this caſe wee muſt not love our ſelves, nor in ſuch a caſe love our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours as our ſelves. For then muſt wee hate our ſelves unto
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:478:54"/> the death, and ours both<note place="margin">Ioh. 12. 25. Apoc. 12. 10. Luke. 14. 26. Math. 24, 16. Deut. 33. 9</note> things, and perſons. It is a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, then <hi>to deny our ſelves:</hi> and it was the practiſe of <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi, not to ſee his father and his mother, nor to acknowledge his brethren.</hi> But if the love of our ſelves be right, and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, then muſt wee love our ſelves, and others as our ſelves.</p>
            <p>It is worth your notice<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> 2. When ſelfe-love is a right charity. 1 <hi>Vt ſe.</hi>
               </note> then to know, when our love is a right Chriſtian charity? A man may love himſelfe three waies. Firſt, when a man loves himſelfe as himſelfe; this is not good: It makes <hi>ſelfe</hi> a God. But man hath a ſuperiour, at whoſe becke hee muſt ſtand, and fall to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Secondly, when a man<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2 Vt finem principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi> Pro. 16. 4.</note> loves himſelfe <hi>as his principall end.</hi> This is not right neither: for man is made for anothers end, as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>God</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:478:54"/> made all things for himſelfe. Thirdly, when a man loves himſelfe <hi>in order to God:</hi> that<note place="margin">3 In ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ad Deuus.</note> is, when the love of God, and of our ſelves, are ſweetly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate: when we love our ſelves in God, and for God, and his will ſake. This is right chriſtian charity in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede: and then, if thou<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Si noſti diligere teipſum, tunc com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitto tibi proximum quem dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gasſicut teipſum. Auguſt. Quest.</hi> 3 How this rule of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice muſt be carried?</note> knoweſt thus how to love thy ſelfe, I will commit thy neighbour unto thee, whom thou mayeſt love as thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>But now you will aske, <hi>how this rule of juſtice muſt be carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</hi> It is certaine, that foure ſorts of perſons would ill to themſelves: <hi>children, idle perſons, malefactors,</hi> and <hi>male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents. Children</hi> ſee not the benefit of education and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; If they might bee cockered and ſpared, they would doe ſo to others, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:478:55"/> in pang, and paſſion. <hi>Idle perſons</hi> know not the comfort of a ſweating and well ordered life. They goe on themſelves in an unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table courſe, and would that others would doe ſo too, though it end in ruine. <hi>Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors</hi> and ſonnes of <hi>Belial,</hi> not being ſenſible of the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of church, common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and family by lawles courſes, would bee let alone, and would let others alone: therefore doe they cry down reformers as buſie perſons, and no good neighbours. <hi>Malecontents,</hi> ſwelling with pride, and not induring the flouds of oppoſition, care not, with <hi>Abimelech,</hi> and <hi>Spira,</hi> if others would kill them, and with <hi>Potiphera,</hi> if others would diſhoneſt them: and ſo would bee an ill law of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to others.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:478:55"/>
            <p>Therefore you muſt know<note place="margin">Voluntas 1 Inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata.</note> that there is two ſorts of <hi>wills</hi> Firſt, <hi>diſordered wills,</hi> (as moſt are) which would indulgence to all vice: what theſe would have others to doe to them, they muſt not doe to others. For they care not if there were no king in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> if eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man did what hee liſt: when all is in a combuſtion, they would then fiſh in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled waters. Reaſon is clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and the ſhowers of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe would fall upon men. Secondly, there are <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and regulated wills</hi> by the<note place="margin">2 Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta et regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lata.</note> law of juſtice and charity. From theſe <hi>wills</hi> ariſeth this law: If ye have orderly and well governed <hi>wills,</hi> then <hi>what ye would that others ſhould doe to you, even ſo doe yee to them.</hi> Thus (as I could) ye have the power of this law in ſenſe.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:478:56"/>
            <p>And now for the applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<note place="margin">2 The ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of this law. <hi>Minoris criminis rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us eſt iegem ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcire quàm ſpernere. Sal. lib. 4. Terrae fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, nihili nepos. Greg. Naz. Aures omnium pulſo, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientias ſingulo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venio. Auguſt.</hi>
               </note> of it, which is the life of the law, know for certaine, that it brings a leſſe guilt to be ignorant of the law, then when you know it, to cotemn it: therefore bee ſure to bee doing.</p>
            <p>Though man bee <hi>the ſonne of the earth, and the nephew of nothing;</hi> yet God hath given him a law which muſt be kept for uſe: yea God hath made him a law to himſelfe in his juſtice to others: therefore I knocke at all your eares, and would faine talke a little with every conſcience heere pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
            <p>This law of Chriſt and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, might bee an help to us upon many occaſions. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe there fall out a new caſe wherein there is no law to order it; wee muſt not ſay, Ile doe what I luſt: but in
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:478:56"/> want of a law, this muſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, <hi>what yee would that others ſhould doe to you, that doe you to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Suppoſe there be a law, but we are ignorant of it, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>walke by rule,</hi> when wee know it not. Heere have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to this, which wil ſhew the <hi>effect of the laew, written in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 15.</note> 
               <hi>our hearts,</hi> and will worke us to doe well to others, becauſe we would have others not do amiſſe to us.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe we have a known law fitted to our caſe, but it is ſo imperfect that holes of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion offer themſelves to a ruſſet coate. Have then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to this: for of this it may be ſaid, as that <hi>Philoſopher</hi> ſaid of old, when hee was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked what hee had gained by his ſtudy? I have gained this, in briefe, that <hi>what others doe</hi>
               <note place="margin">Summum hoc, quòd quae alij non ſine legibus c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acti fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt, ſponte fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciam.</note> 
               <hi>not, but as compelled by the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:478:57"/> ſtroake and whip of the law, I doe it of my owne accord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Suppoſe ye bee to give re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to others, wee reade of one <hi>Crates,</hi> who gave to his <hi>flatterer</hi> ſix hundred poundes; to his <hi>whore</hi> threeſcore pounds, to his <hi>Cooke</hi> an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred<note place="margin">Diog. Laert. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vita Crat.</note> crownes, to his <hi>Phiſitian</hi> eight groates, to his <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher</hi> (who was his divine) three halfe-pence, and to his <hi>Lawyer</hi> (for his words) fume and ſmoake. But if we walk by this rule, wee will not ſet beſt rates upon baſeſt things, and worſt upon beſt: for by a well ordered will, wee would not bee ſo dealt withall our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe laſtly, wee are to adminiſter puniſhments for others, one puniſhment for all faults were not juſt: neither muſt wee puniſh in life, when a member would ſatisfie;
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:478:57"/> nor in body, when goods are enough; nor in goods, when loſſe of credit is more then ſufficient; nor in much in any thing when a little would ſerv the turne: we muſt look with a charitable eye to <hi>both propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Proportio. 1 Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metica. 2 Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trica.</note> for we would be ſo done unto our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Upon all theſe, or like oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, weare this law before our eyes, as Chriſt and nature would have it, it would bee a <hi>Sampſon</hi> of juſtice, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy princes of <hi>Philiſtins</hi> by heapes.</p>
            <p>But for want of this, as <hi>Theocritus</hi> ſaid, of a great tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,<note place="margin">Incipit verborum flumen, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genij ne gutta qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem.</note> 
               <hi>now beginnes a floud of words, but not a drop of wit:</hi> ſo have wee flouds of accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, aggravations, actions, without a drop of grace or modeſty.</p>
            <p>If wee could take a view of all the law of juſtice knit up
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:478:58"/> in this one, wee might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the world of another world of ſinnes, and ſinnes.</p>
            <p>All inferiours doe lay the honour of ſuperiours in the duſt, from the ſubject under the throne, to the people un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the prieſt, yea to the child in the poore mans cottage, for want of this in power, <hi>what yee would that others ſhould doe to you, that doe you to them.</hi> All malicious, and envious ſtrikers, oppreſſors, wounders, ahd hurters of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and ſpirits, doe prejudice the comfortable lives of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, becauſe they forget <hi>what yee would that others doe to you, that doe you to them.</hi> All adulterous perſons, of luſtfull eyes, hearts, hands, or other members, doe hurt the chaſtity of others, becauſe they contemne this, <hi>what yee would that others ſhould doe to
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:478:58"/> you, that doe you to them.</hi> All truſters in wrong and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, hurt the goods of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; all lyars, backbiters, &amp; ſlanderers hurt the goods, and the truth of others, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they neglect and put in the backe part of the wallet this glorious law, <hi>what yee would that others ſhould doe to you, that do ye to them.</hi> All that rob themſelves of their owne hearts, and ſpoile that ſweete contentment they might have in the God of Love, by vexing themſelves with what others have, doe ſlighte the royall law, <hi>what ye would that others ſhould doe to you, that doe you to them.</hi> Oh the world of tranſgreſſors againſt this law! <hi>Give good manners, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Da bonos mores et legis ſcita pro nobis ſunt. Sal. lib. 5.</note> 
               <hi>the requirings, and ordinances of the law are for us:</hi> but by our wicked lives this is againſt us, and will burne the conſcience like
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:478:59"/> fire in the day of Gods fierce wrath.</p>
            <p>But Ile goe no further then the proper buſineſſe of the day. The honourable <hi>Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> wil bee pleaſed to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that the judgement-ſeate endures not either raſh judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or riper, if it bee over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaide with wickedneſſe. If raſh oathes bee imployed, vexing contentions nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, or ſuites drawne out at length: If judgements like ſome concluſions follow the worſt part of the plea, they know, that <hi>they doe not as they would be done unto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>witneſſe</hi> muſt ſpeake nothing but truth, and the whole truth (as the cauſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires) ſo helpe him God, if he overweigh the wheeles of the clocke to make it ſtrike falſe. If (like <hi>Nauplius</hi> to deceive the <hi>Grecians</hi> homeward) hee
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:478:59"/> ſet up a beacon upon a rocke, and make the judgment ſuffer<note place="margin">Pro 6. 26.</note> ſhipwrack, hee <hi>nouriſheth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions,</hi> and <hi>doth not as hee would be done unto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Iury</hi> muſt finde accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to truth of evidence, elſe life, goods, and liberty, (the precious things of a man) will fall before the injurious: and <hi>then he doth not as he would be done unto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Lawyer</hi> muſt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that of <hi>Salomon, that the gathering of riches by a deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 6. 26.</note> 
               <hi>tongue, is vanity toſſed too and fro by them that ſeeke death.</hi> But if hee ſpeake good of evil, and evil of good, hee <hi>doth not as hee would be done unto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Plaintife</hi> muſt not load with falſe accuſations, as<note place="margin">1 King. 21 9. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Iezabel</hi> who accuſed <hi>Nabeth</hi> of blaſphemy; the <hi>Iewes</hi> who accuſed Chriſt of forbidding
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:478:60"/> to pay tribute to <hi>Caeſar;</hi> and<note place="margin">1 Kin. 21. 9. 10. Luk. 23. 2. Act. 24. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullus</hi> who in a ſtarched ſpeech preſented <hi>Paul</hi> to be a peſtilence. If hee doe, he <hi>doth not as hee would bee done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Defendant</hi> muſt not colour his fault with falſe gloſſes againſt conſcience, or deny it when his ſinnes are on his skirts, and written in his forehead, or refuſe any le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal tryall. If hee doe, hee <hi>doth not as hee would bee done unto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Regiſter</hi> muſt preſerve faithfull records, and <hi>not cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and illegally take off what is legally put on</hi> for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of vice &amp; maintenance of vertue. If he doe, hee <hi>doth not as hee would be done unto.</hi> Oh how hard is it to bee a good naturaliſt! much harder to be a good Chriſtian in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving this one law of juſtice</p>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:478:60"/>
            <p>But that yee may doe bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<note place="margin">2 Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions for the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of this law.</note> according to the full bent of this law, receive but a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble inſtruction. Firſt, yee muſt bee <hi>extraordinary perſons.</hi> As it is with a batte or <hi>flinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſe,</hi> it is a kinde of bird, but an extraordinary one. It flies<note place="margin">1 Be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perſons.</note> like a bird, and ſo is among the fowles of the aire; but it brings not forth young like a bird, nor feedes them like a bird, nor feedes it ſelfe like a bird: ſo be <hi>you ſingular</hi> among<note place="margin">Mat. 5. 47.</note> men, one of a city, and two of a tribe. Ordinary men do love the world to a miracle. They forget they are the generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God; and ſo (to the diſhonour of their race) the world and worldly things doe blot out this law of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</p>
            <p>But as wee read of <hi>Hercules</hi> when hee wreſtled with the mighty <hi>Mauritanian Anthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:478:61"/> ſo often as hee threw him to the earth (his mother), hee ſoone recovered his ſtrength againe; but when (beyond ordinary courſe) he lifted him up above the ground, and ſo held him at armes end till he was breathleſſe, hee ſoone vanquiſhed him. So when yee wreſtle with your owne hearts for juſtice (which are <hi>earth, earth, earth</hi>), and throw<note place="margin">Ier 22. 29.</note> them to the ground, ye never goe away conquerours: for they are where they would bee. Therefore lift them up extraordinarily into another element, and have your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations in heaven, and yee ſhall ſoone gaine the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to doe this law of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</p>
            <p>The prudent ſearchers of nature, conſider the ſoule of man according to the three powers of it, and ſpeake
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:478:61"/> (though not ſo accurately as others) of three parts of it: The <hi>reaſonable, angry,</hi> and<note place="margin">1 Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalis. 1 Iraſcibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis. 3 Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcibilis.</note> 
               <hi>luſtfull</hi> part. From the <hi>reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable</hi> part proceeds reaſon it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <hi>judgment, diſcretion,</hi> and <hi>wiſedome;</hi> and this they ſeat in the head. From the <hi>angry</hi> part, iſſue the hot motions of fortitude and courage; and this they ſeate in the heart. From the <hi>lustfull</hi> part, come deſires and appetites after meate, drinke, and other plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; and this they ſeate in the ventricle.</p>
            <p>Theſe three may repreſent unto us, the three ages of the world. In the firſt, they<note place="margin">Melanch. poſt.</note> were wiſe; then wiſedome flouriſhed, arts and ſciences, were invented: and if wee ſeeme to be more in this then they, it is becauſe we are <hi>Pig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> upon thoſe <hi>Giants</hi> ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. In the ſecond, they
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:478:62"/> were valorous. From <hi>Ninus</hi> to <hi>Iulius</hi> was the age of war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious. Then <hi>David, Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Achilles,</hi> and <hi>Hercules</hi> were in prime. But in this third and laſt age, moſt are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to appetite. The under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and heart have had their times, but now the <hi>Belly</hi> is the great God: and as hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger after pleaſure, profit, or honour prevailes, ſo all lawes of God and nature are more or leſſe neglected. Had yee not neede then to be ſingular (now) if you <hi>would doe, as you would be done unto?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, being ſingular &amp;<note place="margin">2 Let the Spirit of Chriſt dwell in you.</note> extraordinary, <hi>let the ſpirit of Chriſt dwell in you,</hi> as well as the law of nature; even that ſpirit wherewith hee did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive this. Nature is a good miſtreſſe, if Chriſt be our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. Nature ſhall well direct us in our workes of juſtice,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:478:62"/> when by Chriſts ſpirit we are created to good works. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bee ſure that you bee in Chriſt by faith, &amp; that Chriſt be in you by the life of juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, ſanctification, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: and then as Chriſt tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth this law of nature, ſo you, through Chriſt, ſhall grow more and more aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the practiſe of it, ſo long as you are.</p>
            <p>Experience teacheth that a tree lives longer then a man, or fowle, or beaſt; and wee aske the reaſon of it; It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved<note place="margin">S. Fr. Bac. Nat. Hiſt.</note> thus. Other creatures grow to their full ſtature, and then grow no more but in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements, as haires, nailes, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and the like: but a tree, (live it never ſo long) growes in proper parts, and ſo drawes juice and ſap, from the roote, thorough the whole body to quicken it.</p>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:478:63"/>
            <p>So if you inquire why a man in Chriſt doth keepe all lawes better then another man? I anſwer, becauſe he is never at his height ſo long as hee is heere. He dayly ſucks in, and drawes (in his growing parts of greatneſſe or good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) the heavenly oyle, and liquor of Chriſts ſpirit, which<note place="margin">Phil. 4.</note> inables him <hi>to doe all things thorough him that helpeth him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Be it (in the name of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi>) thus with you; and ye ſhall not faile to doe as you would be done unto in minds, mouthes, and members. Ile<note place="margin">Motives to obſerve this law.</note> give you but two incentives, and ſo an end.</p>
            <p>The not doing this, will <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> much diſcomfort you in the day of death. In many caſes betwixt you and others, you have ſeene, or heard, variety of opinions: and for want of
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:478:63"/> judgement or goodneſſe (by witty evaſions) have beene ſwayed this way, and that way. But then, let conſcience have her perfect work, and when it ſpies that, by theſe means, ye have not done as ye would be done unto, it cries, &amp; prickes, and wounds, and yee know not what to doe, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when death comes to draw you to the barie of God. Therefore as <hi>Pythagoras</hi> gave a precept to his ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, <hi>not to taſte of any thing that had blacke tailes:</hi> ſo doe I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe you here, and I pray God you may follow it in my chriſtian ſenſe.</p>
            <p>The king, ſaith (according to the old picture) <hi>I rule you all:</hi> the ſouldier ſaith, <hi>I fight for you all:</hi> the husbandman ſaith, <hi>I feede you all:</hi> the prieſt ſaith, <hi>I pray for you all:</hi> but death ſaith, <hi>I devoure you all.</hi>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:478:64"/> And then, if notwithſtanding your pretence of faith in Chriſt, you have impenitent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, not done, as you would be done unto, hell will ſay, <hi>I will torment you all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, conſider that the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> doing of this, will comfort you when that day comes. Put caſe yee have not had braines to ſearch into every particular caſe, to reach to the depth of every wiſe law, to untie every knot in things to bee done or forborne; yet, if in indighting, witneſſing, pleading, anſwering, judging, and recording, yee have done as yee would bee done unto; then ſhall your <hi>memories</hi> bleſſe your underſtandings for ſeeing; your <hi>underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings</hi> bleſſe your memories for recording; your <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings</hi> and <hi>memories,</hi> bleſſe your wills for decreeing;
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:478:64"/> your <hi>wills</hi> bleſſe your affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for maintaining; the whole ſoule bleſſe the body for practiſing; and God ſhall bleſſe all for cleaving unto his law of juſtice from Chriſt, and nature. And if with this you have alſo the law of faith, and piety, and follow them according to the rule of Chriſt, then ſhall you heare, <hi>well done good and faithfull ſervants, enter into your maſters joy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which joy our good <hi>God</hi> bring us all in his good time, thorough his way of piety and juſtice: without holineſſe no man ſhall ſee thee, <hi>O Lord;</hi> therefore bring us thither thorough the way of piety. Hee that doth not righteouſneſſe, is not of thee, <hi>O God;</hi> therefore bring us thither by the way of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe alſo. Oh let us ſerve
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:478:65"/> thee heere in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe all the dayes of our lives, that in the end, when wee ſhall come as a ſhocke of corne to thy barne, wee may bee happy in thee, thorough <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> our <hi>Lord:</hi> to whom with thee and the bleſſed ſpirit, bee all <hi>Kingdome, Power,</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> now and for ever.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:478:65"/>
            <head>THE CHRISTIANS THRIFT IN KEE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PING: OR TWO SERMONS Preached on 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 19.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Holding faith, and a good Conſcience.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He men of the world are much for keeping, the father preſſeth his ſonne, the maſter his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, the friend his friend, <hi>to keepe.</hi> They would have them keep their houſes, keepe their land, keepe their ſtockes, keep
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:478:66"/> their credit, <hi>keepe ſurely what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 20.</note> 
               <hi>they can get honeſtly.</hi> This is among the beſt.</p>
            <p>The Chriſtian muſt bee for keeping too. Hee knowes <hi>whom hee hath truſted,</hi> and<note place="margin">2 Tim. 1. 12</note> would faine have him <hi>keepe his ſoule</hi> to the day of Chriſt. And becauſe hee keepes not them that do not keep them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and <hi>ſave their ſoules</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 2. 40</note> 
               <hi>from this froward generation wherein they live:</hi> therefore hee deſires to doe it himſelfe, and to preſſe every member elſe within his reach, to this golden rule, which bleſſed <hi>Paul</hi> gives to his beloved <hi>Timothy, keep, or hold faith, and a good conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A brave worke, worthy a Chriſtian! If there had beene a better, <hi>Paul</hi> would have ſet it upon <hi>Timothies</hi> ſoul. Other things hee preſſeth unto: but if hee give him a thouſand
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:478:66"/> taskes, of divers matters, if this doe not give life and forme to them all, they may doe others good, but they ſhal doe them none: therefore be thou <hi>holding, faith, and a good conſcience;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Timothy</hi> was a brave young ſparke of grace, blowne up to a great blaze in the church of God. He had ſo well approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved himſelfe to men, and God looked upon him with ſo right an eye, that there went about <hi>prophecies</hi> of him, for the great uſe the Church ſhould have of him, and the manly ſervice hee ſhould doe to God. <hi>Paul</hi> therefore<note place="margin">ver. 18.</note> puts him in minde of them, and provokes him to take ſuch a courſe as may make them good, by <hi>holding faith, and a good conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to raiſe him up to a greater vigilancy, he ſets be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:478:67"/> him ſome that had <hi>made ſhipwrack</hi> of them, together with their puniſhment, and<note place="margin">ver. 20.</note> end of it.</p>
            <p>This is the ſcope then, to provoke <hi>Timothy</hi> to hold whatſoever may be uſeful un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, to make his imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the church comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table unto him, <hi>he muſt hold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you ſay, hee muſt onely <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>have them;</hi> for ſo the word <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> ſoundeth: I anſwer, ſo to have, as to hold. As when (Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,) that wee thorough patience and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the ſcriptures <hi>might have hope,</hi> that is, hold it tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the whole courſe of life for uſe.</p>
            <p>If you ſay, it is enough to <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> pro <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Rom. 15. 4</note> hold them for the preſent. I anſwer, no: it is in ſuch a part of ſpeech, as ſignifieth a continual act, holding today, tomorrow, and for ever.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:478:67"/> Therefore in <hi>Timothies</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, it commends theſe two ſavoury rules of life unto you; that when yee have faith, <hi>ye muſt hold it,</hi> and when yee have a good conſcience, <hi>ye muſt hold it too.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yee muſt hold faith.</hi> Faith is<note place="margin">1 Yee m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt hold faith. Gal. 5. 22. 1 Theſ. 5. 19. Apoc 3. 3</note> of a flying nature in it ſelfe. It is but <hi>a fruit of the ſpirit,</hi> and wee are apt <hi>to quench it.</hi> But as <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith to the church of <hi>Sardis, remember how thou haſt received and heard, and hold faſt:</hi> and to the church of <hi>Philadelphia, hold that faſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 3. 11</note> 
               <hi>which thou haſt, that no man take thy crowne:</hi> ſo be you all ſure to hold faith.</p>
            <p>I ſhall labour (with Gods<note place="margin">1 How yee muſt hold faith.</note> helpe) to cleare theſe two particulars, how ye muſt hold faith, and why ye muſt doe it. Firſt, as hee that would hold his poſſeſſion and inheritance muſt have a good <hi>ground of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:478:68"/> tenure;</hi> his right by gift pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe,<note place="margin">By hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</note> or deſcent; a good <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of tenure,</hi> his deedes and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences; a good <hi>act of te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure,</hi> to ſay with confidence this is mine; and a good <hi>power</hi> to uſe it as his owne for his proper benefit. So if yee would <hi>hold faith,</hi> yee muſt hold</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 The ground of faith.</item>
               <item>2 The object of faith.</item>
               <item>3 The act of faith, and</item>
               <item>4 The power of faith.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The ground of faith, is<note place="margin">1 The ground of faith.</note> your ſaving right to it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which you have nothing to doe with faith to ſave you. And what is that? it is an <hi>humbled ſoule:</hi> none have right to faith to ſave them but ſuch. To make a looſe and broken ground the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of an houſe, is the next way to ſee the ruine of it: but to make a broken heart
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:478:68"/> the ground of faith is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way to ſee it hold. <hi>Come unto me all yee that are weary</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 11.</note> 
               <hi>and heavy laden:</hi> if ye be ſuch, then build upon me for the <hi>reſt of your ſoules.</hi> God carried the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> fourty yeares thorough the wilderneſſe <hi>to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 8. 23</note> 
               <hi>humble them, prove them;</hi> and to make them ſuffer hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and then hee fed them with <hi>Mannah.</hi> God makes the houſe of <hi>David</hi> looke up<note place="margin">Zach. 12. 10. 11.</note> to <hi>Christ</hi> pierced, and <hi>mourne</hi> as a woman mourneth for her onely ſonne: and then in that day hee <hi>opens a</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 13. 1</note> 
               <hi>fountaine</hi> for the houſe of <hi>David,</hi> and the inhabitants of <hi>Ieruſalem, for ſinne, and for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe.</hi> The Holy Ghoſt convinceth the world of <hi>ſin,</hi> and then of <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 16. 8. 9 10. 11.</note> that Chriſt hath fully ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, becauſe hee is aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: and then of <hi>Iudgement,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:478:69"/> to ſet up a throne and caſt out Satan by degrees. Even as phyſicians do firſt purge to pul downe rebelling humours, and then give cordials: So God firſt whips by the <hi>School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>master of the law,</hi> and then<note place="margin">Gal. 3. 24.</note> brings us to Chriſt: this is the ground of faith.</p>
            <p>The object of faith is, the<note place="margin">2 The ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of faith.</note> deedes and evidences of it, <hi>the whole word of God.</hi> There are no other deedes and eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſaving faith but there. Theſe are the <hi>teſtimonies,</hi> and <hi>records</hi> of God: <hi>hee that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeveth</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 5. 10</note> 
               <hi>not God, and his record which he hath witneſſed, hath made him a lyar.</hi> This is that for which God lookes to bee credited. A very knave looks to bee credited for his pawne or bond; an honeſt man for his honeſty; a noble man for his honour; a Prince for his word: much more God. Ye
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:478:69"/> muſt therefore looke to the <hi>Precepts</hi> of God like <hi>David:</hi> who when he tooke notice of<note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 4 5.</note> Gods commandements, given to be kept, hee had an heroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call motion to doe more then hee could, hee prayes that hee might <hi>be taught</hi> them, that he might keepe them, and <hi>bee</hi>
               <note place="margin">ver. 48.</note> 
               <hi>quickned</hi> by them, and reſolves to lift up his hands to Gods commandements, which hee had loved, to doe them. Yee muſt looke to the Judgments and threatnings of God, as the <hi>Ninevites,</hi> who were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently<note place="margin">Ion. 3. 2 Chro. 34. 27.</note> in ſackcloth, and <hi>Ioſiah</hi> who rent his cloathes, with weeping eies, and melting heart. Thus <hi>Davids</hi> fleſh trembled for fear of God, and<note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 120.</note> 
               <hi>he was affraid of his judgments,</hi> yee muſt looke to the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of God as <hi>David: who hid</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 11</note> 
               <hi>them in his heart that he might not ſinne against him.</hi> What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is in the word, ye muſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:478:70"/> have an eie unto. For though they doe not ſo immediately concerne you in the way of life and death (as many Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alogies, Chronologies, Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and Prophecies) yet you muſt <hi>bee ready</hi> to underſtand<note place="margin">Praepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi.</note> them and their uſes as God ſhall offer them: yet yee muſt principally hold <hi>precepts</hi> to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, <hi>threatnings</hi> to humble, and <hi>promiſes</hi> to allure and comfort; ye muſt hold them, by <hi>underſtanding what the will</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 17</note> 
               <hi>of the Lord is,</hi> till (if ye can) yee come to <hi>all riches of the ful</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 2. 2.</note> 
               <hi>aſſurance of underſtanding.</hi> Yee muſt hold them by <hi>aſſenting</hi> to them: yeelding to all the truth of them, as Saint <hi>Luke</hi> to the ſtorie of Chriſt where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he was <hi>fully perſwaded.</hi> Yee<note place="margin">Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e 1. 1.</note> muſt hold them, by bringing your bodies and ſoules into ſubjection unto them. For in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> neither circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:478:70"/> availeth any thing, nor uncircumciſion, but <hi>faith wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 6.</note> 
               <hi>by love.</hi> This is the object of faith.</p>
            <p>The act of faith, is to ſay,<note place="margin">3 The act of faith.</note> 
               <hi>this is mine:</hi> to adjudge and appropriate father, ſonne, and holy Ghoſt unto your ſelves; without this yee cannot feele any comfort of what you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve. Therefore as <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid, <hi>My God, My</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 22. 1. Ioh. 20. 28</note> 
               <hi>God:</hi> as <hi>Thomas</hi> ſaid, <hi>My Lord,</hi> and <hi>my God:</hi> and as the<note place="margin">Luke 1. 47</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed Virgine</hi> ſaid, <hi>my ſpirit</hi> (that is the quinteſſence of my ſoule acted by the ſpirit of God) <hi>rejoyceth in God my Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our:</hi> ſo by way of adherence, (when moſt times ye have no evidence) yee muſt take God in Chriſt as your owne, as hee offers himſelfe. <hi>I am the Lord</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ex. 20. Ier. 31.</note> 
               <hi>thy God, I will bee thy God.</hi> This is the act of faith.</p>
            <p>The power of faith, is to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:478:71"/> make uſe of the riches of it<note place="margin">The pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of faith. Pſal. 32. Pſal. 45. Rom. 4. Act. 15. Mal. 4. Eph. 3. Heb. 6. 2 Cor. 4. 13.</note> for thy owne proper good. Great is the power of faith, and it prevaileth. It <hi>covereth</hi> our ſinnes by the garments of Chriſt our elder brother, and ſo is <hi>imputed to us for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</hi> It <hi>cureth</hi> our ſinnes, bringing Chriſt, who hath <hi>healing under his wings,</hi> to <hi>dwell in our hearts by faith.</hi> It brings forth a world of the <hi>labour of love,</hi> wee having the ſame <hi>ſpirit of faith,</hi> believe, &amp; ſpeak, and thinke, and doe. For by<note place="margin">Eph. 2. 10.</note> faith we are Gods workeman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <hi>created in Chriſt to good workes,</hi> to walke in them. And this affirme conſtantly that they <hi>that have believed in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 3. 8.</note> GOD, <hi>be carefull to maintaine good workes.</hi> This is the power of faith.</p>
            <p>Now, this ground of faith,<note place="margin">2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Why yee muſt hold faith.</note> this object of faith, this act of faith this power of faith, you
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:478:71"/> muſt hold upon theſe five Grounds.</p>
            <p>Firſt, faith is our life; <hi>wee live by faith,</hi> not by ſight; and<note place="margin">1 Faith our life. 2 Cor. 5. Hab. 2.</note> every juſt man muſt <hi>live by his faith.</hi> Not <hi>efficiently:</hi> for ſo, <hi>in</hi> GOD <hi>we live,</hi> move, and<note place="margin">Act. 17.</note> have our being. Nor <hi>meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly:</hi> for ſo ſaith Chriſt, <hi>I am the way, the truth and the life.</hi> Nor by way of imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.</note> application: for ſo the holy ghoſt is <hi>a quickening ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> as <hi>Adams</hi> ſoule was the<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 18. Gen. 2.</note> breath of life. But as a prime inſtrument of our life in Chriſt, without this wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have life, either <hi>before God</hi> or in this <hi>miſerable world.</hi> This<note place="margin">Rom. 1. 17 Heb. 10. 38</note> unites us to Chriſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives a quickning ſpirit (as the vertue of Chriſt), from the ſpirit of Chriſt, in the meanes of ſalvation. As men ſay of their trades, and hands, under God, <hi>they are my living,</hi> take away theſe, and take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:478:72"/> my life: ſo ſay wee of faith: it is your life: therfore hold it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, faith is our <hi>power</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Faith is our power of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</note> 
               <hi>of working,</hi> to doe us our beſt good. In a naturall man, his reaſon is his power. Hee is borne naked, with abundance of bodily weakneſſe; a beaſt hath a great deale of bodily ſtrength: and if a lyon ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally knew how to uſe his pawes, a dog his teeth, a bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock, or buck his hornes, or an horſe his hoofes, how few men would there bee in the world? But let man come in with his reaſon, and hee ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dues them all. But in a belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his faith is his power: and what is the power of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to this? As Chriſt ſaid of miraculous faith, it pulls up trees by the rootes, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moves mountaines, it makes ſunne ſtand ſtill, and go back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:478:72"/> ſo much more of this ſaving chriſtian faith in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kinde. It covers more ſinnes then heaven and earth can cover. Get the heavens to cover them: our ſinnes are more then the ſtarres, and <hi>are come up above the heavens.</hi> Get the ſea to cover them: the ſea can cover the ſands at a full tide, but our ſins are <hi>more then the ſandes of the ſea.</hi> Get the earth, and all the creatures to cover them: our ſinnes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-top them all, and make<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> the whole <hi>creation groane</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the burthen. But get faith, and as love covers <hi>a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of ſinnes</hi> in others, ſo faith covers all ſinnes in our ſelves. It brings the garments of Chriſt, and then <hi>wee cannot</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 16. Phil. 3. Dan. 9.</note> 
               <hi>bee naked.</hi> It brings the <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes of God,</hi> the <hi>everlaſting righteouſneſſe</hi> to dwel amongſt men, and then, God cannot
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:478:73"/> but be there, where his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe is, to <hi>give grace and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 84: 16</note> 
               <hi>glorie,</hi> and every perfect gift. It is your power to doe your beſt good, and therefore hold it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, faith <hi>is your work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi>
               <note place="margin">3 Faith is our work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</note> Set faith about any work, and what can it not doe? Art thou at Gods<note place="margin">Gen. 12.</note> word, to goe a great journey, thou knoweſt not whither? Faith did it for <hi>Abraham.</hi> Art thou to fight againſt ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,<note place="margin">Heb. 11. Gen. 22.</note> beares, <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther puiſſant enemies? Faith did it for <hi>David, Sampſon, Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deon, Barach,</hi> and their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes. Art thou to doe what nature abhorres? Faith did it for <hi>Abraham</hi> in the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of his ſon. Art thou to cleanſe the uncleane ſtables of ſinne? Faith will take Chriſts ſpirit, and arguments, and doe it. It cries out, <hi>ſhall I
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:478:73"/> that am dead to ſinne yet live</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6:</note> 
               <hi>therein? Shall I ſinne that grace may abound?</hi> God forbid: I will mortifie <hi>the deedes of the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> 
               <hi>fleſh by the ſpirit.</hi> Art thou to ſuffer perſecution?</p>
            <p>Faith will ſuffer it for thee in <hi>goates-skinnes,</hi> and <hi>ſheepes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skinnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> in the craggie wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Art thou to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>Death,</hi> and <hi>Hell?</hi> Faith will doe it too. Faith <hi>receives</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> 
               <hi>the dead to life;</hi> and ſends a defiance to the greateſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of it, <hi>O Death, where is</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15:</note> 
               <hi>thy ſting? O Hell, where is thy victory? Thankes bee to God for Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> the Captaine of my ſalvation. O who would bee without faith! It is our workeman, <hi>hold it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7. 4 Faith is our beſt light here.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, faith is <hi>all the comfortable light,</hi> yee have in the world. Without the ſunne the earth would be an <hi>Aegypt,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:478:74"/> and without faith we are in <hi>a region of darkeneſſe.</hi> The wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men<note place="margin">Math. 4. Math. 2.</note> came out of the eaſt and worſhipped Chriſt, offering alſo gold, frankincenſe, and myrrhe: why? what did they ſee in him? They ſaw a child, not a man: they ſaw him in a ſtable, not in a throne, in ragges, not in robes, crying in a cratch, not thundring in the clouds; how then came it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout they now worſhipped? Faith ſaw God in him, for the heavens waited upon him in his ſtarre. Faith ſaw in him a prophet, a prieſt, a king, and their oblations were anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. The thiefe upon the croſſe cryes out unto Chriſt, <hi>Lord remember mee when thou comeſt into thy kingdome?</hi> was he a Lord that was dealt with like a ſlave? had hee a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome that was diſgracefully thruſt out of the world? Could
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:478:74"/> he remember him, that would not remember himſelf, when they cryed, <hi>come downe from the croſſe,</hi> and ſave thy ſelfe? Faith caſts away theſe miſts, and ſaw glory in ſhame. Yee know what the <hi>Centurion</hi> ſaid, <hi>verily this man was the ſon</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 27. 54.</note> 
               <hi>of God,</hi> what? a man, and the ſonne of God too? The ſon of God, that could not have the favour to live, or dye ſo well as the ſonne of man? Surely, ſome ſparke of faith ſaw life in death, light in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: It is your light, <hi>hold it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, faith makes earth<note place="margin">5 Faith makes earth hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Math. 13. Gen. 28. Eph. 2.</note> heaven unto you, and the church the <hi>kingdom of heaven,</hi> the houſe of God, the <hi>Gates of heaven,</hi> and ſets us on the <hi>ſeats of heaven</hi> heere below. Before we come to the proper place <hi>and manſion,</hi> which Chriſt hath<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.</note> provided for us, by faith wee
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:478:75"/> ſit with <hi>Abraham, Iſaack</hi> and <hi>Iacob</hi> in the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Put caſe wee hope for it, wee ſee it not: <hi>faith is the ground of things hoped for, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>of things not ſeene.</hi> It <hi>ſtands under</hi> the waight of the whole world, and yet ſayes, <hi>heaven is mine.</hi> It ſees nothing but earth, and ſinners, and beaſts, and trees, under the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopie of the ſtarrie heaven, and yet ſayes, <hi>heaven is mine,</hi> as if it had it already. O the world of grace and glory that is in faith! therefore <hi>hold faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh that I now knew how<note place="margin">Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> to ſcrew my ſelfe into your ſoules to ſearch whether yee <hi>hold faith!</hi> How many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands have it not, and cannot hold it? How many thouſands have it a little, and know not whether they hold it or no? yee are to bee married to the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:478:75"/> lambe, and till that day come,<note place="margin">Annulum ſponſalem.</note> yee have but the <hi>wedding-ring</hi> of faith, to have and to hold, firſt for promiſe, then for frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Tell me then:</p>
            <p>Doe yee hold the <hi>ground of</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Try the ground of faith Rom. 8.</note> 
               <hi>faith?</hi> Then yee are humbled ſoules: yee have paſſed tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the <hi>ſpirit of bondage,</hi> whereby yee have been ſhut up in priſon under <hi>Moſes,</hi> till <hi>the ſonne hath made you free,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.</note> and yee walke humbly ever after for feare of looſing this eſtate. This laies the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of faith deepe enough. <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1. 20.</note> built upon the ſands, and ſo they <hi>ſhip-wrackt</hi> againſt the rockes of the world. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you muſt downe lower, under the ſands, earth, rockes, to the gates of hell, and then, <hi>Out of the depths have I cryed</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 130. 1</note> 
               <hi>unto thee O Lord.</hi> Are yee thus in ſome meaſure, or other,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:478:76"/> according to your ſinnes? Say it if yee love faith and your ſalvation. Are yee <hi>convinced</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 16. Act. 2.</note> 
               <hi>of your ſinnes?</hi> are yee <hi>pricked at the heart</hi> for your ſinnes? Are yee ſo all this, that yee are at utter enmity with all ſinne? Then keepe this ground of faith.</p>
            <p>Doe yee hold the object of<note place="margin">2 Try the object of faith.</note> faith? This nouriſheth and keepes faith alive. It is like oyle to the lampe, like fewell to the fire, and like ſap to the tree. Have you full aſſurance of the knowledge of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures? Can you ſay, Ile pawn my life, body, and goods, and ſoule, that, though I cannot conceive all, yet all in the ſcripture is true? what I know is true, and I reſolve to learne more: what I know not is true, and I will doe my beſt to comprehend that too. Have ye a free aſſent to all the truth
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:478:76"/> of it, and <hi>to that alone for ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation?</hi> Do ye not come off baſely as <hi>Agrippa, almost thou</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 26. 28</note> 
               <hi>perſwadeſt mee?</hi> Have yee a beliefe to all the precepts, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and threatnings of the ſcriptures? Doe ye ſay all the commandements are true, &amp; I muſt do them: all the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings are true, and if I live in<note place="margin">Deut. 32.</note> ſinne, I muſt undergoe them, even to burning <hi>in the nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt hell:</hi> all the promiſes are true, and I muſt relieve my flagging and drooping ſpirit with them, in deſpite of my unbeleeving heart? Doth thy faith in the knowledge of them change thee, as it did <hi>David<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> who when hee could<note place="margin">Pſal. 40.</note> ſay, that <hi>in the volume of thy booke it is written of mee</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently cries out, <hi>Loe I come, to doe thy will?</hi> If it be thus, hold faith. But doeſt thou not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hate the <hi>being of the word</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:478:77"/> in thy underſtanding? Thou knoweſt it will ſtrip thee of all thy luſts. Doeſt thou not therefore ſay as thoſe miſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, <hi>depart from mee, I deſire</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 20.</note> 
               <hi>not the knowledge of thy lawes?</hi> doeſt thou not hate the <hi>nature of the word,</hi> to will as that wills? Heare that curſed voice, and feare to finde it in thy ſelfe, <hi>I will doe as I have done,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 44.</note> whatſoever the word of God ſaith. Doeſt thou not hate the rules of the word? Art thou not ſorry they are true: Wouldeſt thou not they were falſe? Can a fleſhly-man love that, <hi>fleſh and bloud cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.</note> 
               <hi>the kingdome of heaven?</hi> Can an old ſinner love that, <hi>the childe ſhall dye an hundred</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſ. 65. 20.</note> 
               <hi>yeares old</hi> (ſo ripe ſhall hee bee for God) <hi>and the ſinner being an hundred yeares old ſhall bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed?</hi> Can an uſurer love that, hee is not for Gods ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:478:77"/> and holy hill, that<note place="margin">Pſal. 15. 5</note> 
               <hi>putteth his mony to uſury?</hi> Can an whoremonger love that, <hi>whoremongers and adulterers</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13.</note> 
               <hi>God will judge?</hi> or any of thoſe ſinners that, <hi>bee not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued; neither fornicators, nor</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 9 10.</note> 
               <hi>idolaters, nor adulterers, nor ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feminate, nor abuſers of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with mankind, nor theevs, nor covetous, nor drunkards, nor revilers, nor extortiouers, ſhall inherit the kingdome of God?</hi> If they love not the nature, being, and rules of the object of faith, this is not to hold faith.</p>
            <p>Doe yee hold the act of<note place="margin">3 Try the act of faith.</note> faith? Doe yee reſt with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence upon the promiſes of God in Chriſt? ye pule and crie in the ſorrow of your hearts (even when your ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row hath turned you to God) and ſay, I know not what to doe. This yee doe; but yee
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:478:78"/> looke not upon the new and everlaſting covenant, and ſay, God is mine, Chriſt is mine, the holy Ghoſt is mine, and I <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> am his. Alas, ſay you; I am <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> not worthy. Surely there ſhould not have beene a ſaint in heaven, nor out of hell, by this argument. Though your willfull unworthineſſe will diſcard you, yet God tyes not himſelfe to you by your worth, but his owne. Oh therefore <hi>hold faith,</hi> as <hi>Iacob</hi> did God, <hi>I will not let thee goe</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 32. 26. Ruth. 1.</note> 
               <hi>except thou bleſſe mee:</hi> and as <hi>Ruth</hi> did <hi>Naomi, whitherſoever thou goest,</hi> I will go with thee both in life and death.</p>
            <p>Doe yee hold the power of<note place="margin">4 Try the power of faith. Rom. 16. Iames 2.</note> faith? Say then, what doth it make thee to doe? Shew the <hi>obedience of faith:</hi> ſhew me thy <hi>faith by thy workes.</hi> It is as the plummet on the clock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line which makes you ſtrike.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:478:78"/> It will make you looke upon <hi>ſinne which pierced Christ,</hi> and<note place="margin">Zach. 12.</note> mourne for it, and caſt it out (as <hi>Agar</hi> the bond-woman) with a, <hi>Get thee hence.</hi> It is in thee as in the ſea, there is that <hi>Leviathan and creeping things innumerable:</hi> ſo there are in<note place="margin">Pſal. 104. 25, 26.</note> thee, maſter ſinnes, and cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping luſts innumerable: but let faith looſe upon them, and then as when God made man after his Image, he ſaid, <hi>let him have dominion over the fiſh of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 1. 26</note> 
               <hi>the ſea, and every creeping thing:</hi> ſo doth God ſay to faith, <hi>bee it unto thee as thou believeſt,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven<note place="margin">Math. 15.</note> againſt the whole hoaſte of ſinne. It will make you looke upon Chriſt and love him above all, and delight in all that belong unto him, the word of faith, the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of faith, the ſeales of faith, the houſhold of faith, for it will not let you ſtroake the head, and ſtrike the body:
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:478:79"/> yea, it will make you deſire the appearance of the <hi>Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> that yee may be with him for ever: you will ſtay his leaſure, but with winged de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>O make haſte my beloved, and bee like the Roe: come Lord</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 8. 14 Apoc. 22.</note> 
               <hi>Ieſus, come quickly.</hi> It will make you look upon God the father, and depend upon him <hi>for all things,</hi> (for faith reaſons thus, <hi>if he have given mee Chriſt, how ſhall hee not</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> 
               <hi>with him give us all things al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo?</hi>) yea, and ſubmit unto him <hi>in all things,</hi> (for the children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> will <hi>doe the workes</hi> of <hi>Abraham;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 8, Gal. 3. 7</note> and they which <hi>are of the faith</hi> are the children of <hi>Abraham</hi>): yea, and <hi>goe boldly to the throne</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 4. 16</note> 
               <hi>of grace,</hi> that yee may have his ſtrength to doe all obedience, and to truſt in him <hi>in hardeſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 13. 15</note> 
               <hi>times.</hi> It will make you look to God the holy Ghoſt, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:478:79"/> ſubmit to his worke of convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and converſion, yea, and to do whatſoever he enableth unto. Hee is the great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of faculties, who <hi>helpeth</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> 
               <hi>your infirmities:</hi> you take his help by faith and doe it. It will make you looke upon your ſelves, and worke the worke of God upon your ſoules with power. The fowles <hi>pick-up the good</hi> ſeede ſo ſoone as it is<note place="margin">Luke 8.</note> ſowne, becauſe <hi>it is not mixed with faith:</hi> but the word<note place="margin">Heb. 4. 2 1 Theſ. 2 13.</note> 
               <hi>workes effectually</hi> in you that believe. Yea, it will make you fight the battels of God inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perably. When <hi>Paul</hi> came to <hi>Epheſus, there aroſe no ſmall ſtirre about that way:</hi> ſo when<note place="margin">Act 19. 23 Math. 2.</note> faith in Chriſt comes, <hi>Herod is troubled, and all Ieruſalem:</hi> but faith makes you like the houſe of <hi>David, grow stronger and</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 3. 1</note> 
               <hi>ſtronger,</hi> and ſin like the houſe of <hi>Saul, grow weaker and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker:</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:478:80"/> It makes you like <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 30. 8</note> who wreſtled with the wreſtlings of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed. Let the world fight againſt you: <hi>this is your victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 15. 4 1 Pet. 5. 8</note> 
               <hi>even your faith.</hi> Let Satan come; reſiſt him, ſtedfaſt in the faith. Let the fleſh come; as thoſe beaſts had <hi>their domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 7. 12</note> taken from them, yet <hi>their lives</hi> were prolonged: ſo faith ſpoiles the fleſh of her Kingdome, though it muſt live as a <hi>Iebuſite.</hi> Let God himſelfe deſert and forſake thee, yeth faith ſaith, <hi>though</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 13. 15</note> 
               <hi>thou kill mee I will truſt in thee.</hi> Laſtly, faith will make you looke upon your brethren, and fill you <hi>with mercy and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit 3 8. Eph. 2 9, 10</note> 
               <hi>good workes.</hi> When <hi>Dorcas</hi> believed, ſhee <hi>made coates</hi> and <hi>garments</hi> to cloath the naked.<note place="margin">Act 9. 39</note> When <hi>Tyrus</hi> was to believe, ſhee would nor treaſure up merchandiſe, <hi>but get it for
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:478:80"/> them that dwell before the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſ. 23. 18.</note> 
               <hi>to eate ſufficiently, and for dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cloathing.</hi> When the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples were taught to forgive their brethren, they cried out, <hi>Lord increaſe our faith;</hi> as if<note place="margin">Luke 17. 4</note> they ſhould ſay, faith will doe it: the more faith, the more mercy; for if you believe your owne ten thouſands forgiven, you will forgive others tens: yea, when you looke upon your brethren, faith will move you to draw them to Chriſt. It ſets you upon the high mountaines, which doe make the vallies fat with the drops that deſcend from them, <hi>when</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 22.</note> 
               <hi>thou art converted, ſtrengthen thy brethen,</hi> ſaith Chriſt to <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> If <hi>Andrew</hi> have found Chriſt, hee calls <hi>Peter;</hi> If <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> have met with him he cals<note place="margin">Iohn. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nathanael.</hi> If thou thus have the power of faith, hold it: If thou have it not, be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:478:81"/> in time, get faith and hold it,</p>
            <p>It may bee thou wilt ſay,<note place="margin">What wee muſt do to hold it.</note> what ſhall I doe to hold it? if then thou wouldſt have all in a word, <hi>ſtop</hi> thine ears againſt the enemies of faith; <hi>I was</hi>
               <note place="margin">In hac fide natus ſum. Auguſt.</note> 
               <hi>born in this faith,</hi> is a loſe plea, it is the gift of God. <hi>Heare</hi> duely the friend of faith, the preaching of the Goſpel. <hi>Pray</hi> the praier of faith in the name of Chriſt. <hi>Vſe</hi> the ſeals of faith, the ſacraments. <hi>Keepe</hi> experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to nouriſh and fatten faith. <hi>Buy</hi> faith, but ſell it not for a thouſand worlds: part with al domineering ſin for it; they that ſet not this price up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on precious faith, ſhall never have it, nor ever hold it. Thus doe and thou ſhalt give glorie to God, and bring comfort to thy own ſoule for ever and for ever,</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:478:81"/>
            <head>THE SECOND SERMON, on 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 19.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>And a good Conſcience.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou have ſeene the holding of faith. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſavoury rule which <hi>Paul</hi> under the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Timothie,</hi> commends unto us is, when wee have a good conſcience to hold that alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yee muſt hold a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As faith is of a flying na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in it ſelfe; ſo is a good
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:478:82"/> conſcience too; it hath many wings to flie away from us, the weake owners of it. It flies<note place="margin">A good conſcience is of a fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nature. 1 By feares</note> away, firſt <hi>by feare, Abraham</hi> was afraid of the court of <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech,</hi> and <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore weakely taught his wife <hi>Sarah</hi> to tell a lye: and <hi>Peter</hi> was afraid in the high-prieſts hall, and he denied his maſter with curſing: <hi>Daniel,</hi> and <hi>the three worthies</hi> baniſhed feare from their ſoules, and would worſhip God alone, and pray unto him what ever came, and ſo kept a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, whereas <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> loſt it. Secondly, <hi>by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifulneſſe: Adonibezeck</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 By un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Iudg. 1. Luke 16.</note> was cruell, and what a wicked conſcience had hee in cutting off the thumbes of ſeaventie Kings, and uſing them like dogges? <hi>Dives</hi> was ſo too, and what a conſcience had he in denying the crumbes of his
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:478:82"/> table? Thirdly, <hi>By the love of</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 By the love of the world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Gal. 6. 12.</note> 
               <hi>the world:</hi> the falſe Apoſtles making a faire ſhew in the fleſh, conſtrained chriſtians to be circumciſed; onely, <hi>leaſt they ſhould ſuffer perſecution</hi> for the croſſe of Chriſt: and thus a good conſcience did fly away. Fourthly, <hi>by the love</hi>
               <note place="margin">4 By love of ſinne.</note> 
               <hi>of ſinne: David</hi> loved the ſweete ſinne of <hi>Bathſhebah;</hi> therefore hee contrived the death of <hi>Vriah,</hi> and ſo conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence fled. Fiftly, <hi>by the love</hi>
               <note place="margin">5 By love of honour.</note> 
               <hi>of honour; Achitophel</hi> was not honoured above <hi>Hushai</hi> the <hi>Archite,</hi> and hee hanged himſelfe. <hi>Adonijah</hi> was not honoured above <hi>Salomon,</hi> and hee ended in rebellion. <hi>Big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> and <hi>Tereſh</hi> had not ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour anſwerable to their minds, and they proved trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous. <hi>Haman</hi> could not have <hi>Mardocaies</hi> knee, and all the Jewes (if hee can helpe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:478:83"/> it) muſt die for it. And thus a good conſcience fled from them. Sixtly, <hi>by the guilt and</hi>
               <note place="margin">6 By the guilt and horrour of ſinne.</note> 
               <hi>horrour of great ſinnes: Iudas</hi> was preſſed ſore with what hee had done, and hee went out and hanged himſelf: and thus a good conſcience did flie from him. Laſtly, <hi>by</hi>
               <note place="margin">7 By profit Pſal. 73. Ier. 12. Iob. 21. 2 Tim. 4 10.</note> 
               <hi>the profits</hi> of the world: <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, Ieremy,</hi> and <hi>Iob</hi> had not the proſperitie of wicked men, and in a paſſion they fel to grumbling againſt God: <hi>Demas</hi> had it caſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> upon him, and forſooke <hi>Paul,</hi> and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced the preſent world: and thus good conſcience was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in the firſt, altogether in the laſt chaſed. What ſhall I ſay? There are ſome ſins <hi>of daily incurſion,</hi> which are la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented,<note place="margin">Peccata quotidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae incurſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis, et vaſtantia conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias.</note> groaned under, and fought againſt, which may bee <hi>lived with,</hi> though not <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in,</hi> and yet a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:478:83"/> may ſtay by us: but if any ſinne <hi>lay waſte the conſcience</hi> by ſelfe-libertie, and preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: good conſcience flies, and therefore hold it.</p>
            <p>To helpe you in this alſo, I<note place="margin">1 How to hold a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note> ſhall labour to ſhew you two things: how you may hold a good conſcience, and why you muſt doe it.</p>
            <p>If yee would hold a good conſcience, yee muſt hold foure things,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 The light of conſcience.</item>
               <item>2 The love of conſcience.</item>
               <item>3 The works of conſcience.</item>
               <item>4 The charge of conſcience.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1 <hi>The light of conſcience</hi> muſt<note place="margin">1 Hold the light of conſcience</note> be held. Be a workeman ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo good, hee cannot ſhew it, if hee want light to doe his worke by: ſo is it with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. Now conſcience hath a double light: 1 the light<note place="margin">1 The light of nature.</note> of nature, which light ſtill preſents ſome principles to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:478:84"/> frame our life by, as that there is a God, that hee is to bee worſhipped, that we muſt doe to others, as wee would bee done unto: and if theſe bee not followed, conſcience checks. 2 The light of the<note place="margin">2 The light of nature.</note> word, which fully preſents the particulars of thoſe gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls, and ſhewes with what, how, and when God is to bee worſhipped: together with that honour, life, honeſtie, goods, truth, and quietneſſe of nature, wherein wee muſt ſo doe to others, as wee would they ſhould doe to us. If yee keepe not both theſe lights, conſcience can never be good.<note place="margin">Three eies view all 1 of God. Heb. 4. Ier. 9.</note> There are three eies that look upon all things done: firſt, the eye of God who hath all things <hi>naked before him.</hi> Hee ſees and <hi>writes with a penne of iron, and point of a diamond:</hi> and either hee cenſures heere,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:478:84"/> or heereafter. Secondly, the<note place="margin">2 Of the world.</note> eye of the world: this ſees all things manifeſted; and would make you believe, thorough ſquinteyed jealouſie and ſuſpition, that it ſees more then it doth, and ſo paſſeth cenſures accordingly. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">3 The eye of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> the eye of conſcience. This ſees all that it is enlightened to ſee: but if it have not light, it ſees not, and cenſures not; therefore hold the light of conſcience.</p>
            <p>The love of conſcience<note place="margin">2 Hold the love of conſcience Gen. 31.</note> muſt be held, If ye love it not, it will away. As <hi>Iacob, when hee ſaw Labans<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> countenance chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and his wages too, and that ten times, away he goes: ſo doth conſcience. As <hi>David</hi> when he ſaw himſelfe not lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the court of <hi>Saul,</hi> away hee goes to the <hi>Philiſtines, Achiſh,</hi> wilderneſſe, any whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther where hee could finde entertainement: ſo will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:478:85"/> deale with you. As therefore yee ſay of that you love, I thanke God for this, I would not bee without it: ſo ſay of conſcience, I thanke God for conſcience, I would not bee without it for a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand worlds: thus hold the love of conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The worke of conſcience</hi> muſt bee held too. It is an officer under God to determine, upon<note place="margin">3 Hold the worke of conſcience</note> information, of all our actions for excuſation, accuſation, conviction, or converſion: and can Gods officers bee idle? The officers of men may bee idle, yea, <hi>foundations may be out of courſe.</hi> The out-ward<note place="margin">Pſal 83.</note> officers of God may bee idle too: magiſtrates and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, may too often be found to bee <hi>idol ſhepheards:</hi> but this privie counſellour, and immediate internall officer,<note place="margin">Zach. 11. 17</note> 
               <hi>conſcience,</hi> cannot bee idle. God ſits on the throne with
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:478:85"/> it, and though it ſeemes to ſleepe, yet in ſtill ſilence it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſters all acts and neglects, omiſſions, and commiſſions; and when a man would think that all is forgotten, then (<hi>In an evill day</hi>) it brings forth all, and <hi>layes it in order before us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.</note> to our ſhame and confuſion. Hold therefore the worke of<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.</note> conſcience; and what is that? It is threefold.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>to propound</hi> unto you from the light of nature, and<note place="margin">The work of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is threefold. 1 To pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound.</note> the word, what yee ought to bee, and doe in the whole frame of life, and courſe of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. It layes the rule of GODS Image, and will, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, and ſayes thus you ſhould bee, and doe ſo and ſo: as to <hi>Adam,</hi> I ſhould not have eaten the forbidden fruit, I ſhould have kept the<note place="margin">Gen. 2.</note> covenant of my God; for hee ſaid, <hi>doe this and live:</hi> to <hi>David:</hi> I ſhould not have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:478:86"/> adultery, or contrived murther; for God hath ſaid, thou ſhalt not doe ſo.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>to apply</hi> (by way<note place="margin">2 To apply</note> of reflection upon themſelvs) what yee have beene, or done. I ſhould have beene, and done ſo, and ſo: but I am, and have done thus and thus. As to <hi>Adam,</hi> I ſhould not have eaten the forbidden fruit; but I have done it: to <hi>David</hi> I ſhould not have committed adultery, and murther; but I have done them: and to all of us, I ſhould have repented, believed, hoped, loved: but I have not done them as I ought.<note place="margin">3 To pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>to pronounce</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall judgement upon your perſons &amp; actions: as therfore I am a wicked man, <hi>have done fooliſhly,</hi> and am accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed:<note place="margin">2 Sam. 24.</note> or therefore I am in Chriſt, have done uprightly,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:478:86"/> and am bleſſed. Thus <hi>David, I</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 119. Luke 1. 5.</note> 
               <hi>have gone aſtray like a loſt ſheep:</hi> thus the prodigal, <hi>I have ſinned againſt heaven and before thee:</hi> thus <hi>Paul, I was a perſecutor, blaſphemer, oppreſſour:</hi> &amp; thus <hi>Hezekiah, I have walked before</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 1. Eſ. 37.</note> 
               <hi>thee with a perfect heart.</hi> This work of conſcience will make you runne out of <hi>Sodom</hi> with a ſhowre of brimſtone at your heeles: or make you paſſe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the wilderneſſe under a cloud of comfortable prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: therefore hold it.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>the charge of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi>
               <note place="margin">4 Hold the charge of conſcience</note> muſt be held alſo. It hath a large Dioceſſe over every ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, and every manifeſt thing of yours in perſon, or by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. It hath a charge over <hi>inclinations. Davids</hi> conſcience ſaw the inclinations &amp; prone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his heart to cleave un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the duſt, and therefore hee flies to GOD, <hi>encline my heart</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:478:87"/> 
               <hi>unto thy teſtimonies,</hi> and not unto covetouſneſſe. It hath charge over the <hi>underſtanding:</hi> therefore <hi>Agurs</hi> conſcience lookes upon that, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines, <hi>ſurely I am more bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 30. 2</note> 
               <hi>then any man, and have not the underſtanding of Adam in mee.</hi> It hath charge over the <hi>memorie:</hi> therefore God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents memory to his people, <hi>they remembred not the Lord</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iud. 8. 34 Pſal. 106. 7</note> 
               <hi>their God: they remembred not the multitude of thy mercies,</hi> that their conſciences might worke accordingly. It hath charge over <hi>thoughts, wills, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſ. 55. 7</note> and <hi>deſires.</hi> Let the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous man forſake his <hi>thoughts,</hi> ſaith God to <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 15.</note> the <hi>thoughts</hi> defile a man, ſaith Chriſt to <hi>conſcience, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, how long ſhall your wicked</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 4, 14.</note> 
               <hi>thoughts lodge within you? yee</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 5.</note> 
               <hi>will not</hi> come unto me that ye may bee ſaved, ſaith Chriſt to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:478:87"/> 
               <hi>conſcience.</hi> Oh how I <hi>love</hi> thy<note place="margin">Pſal. 119. Pſal. 18. Pſal. 119. Pſal. 42.</note> law! yea, I <hi>love thee dearly O Lord my God;</hi> I <hi>hate</hi> all wicked waies (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. My ſoule <hi>longeth</hi> for thee, as the hart panteth after rivers of waters; I <hi>deſire</hi> to be<note place="margin">Phil. 1.</note> diſſolved, &amp; to be with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſay <hi>Davids</hi> and <hi>Pauls</hi> conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences: but wicked mens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences ſhall cry at laſt, wee <hi>deſired</hi> not the knowledge of<note place="margin">Iob. 21.</note> thy lawes. Yea, the charge of <hi>Conſcience</hi> reacheth to your words, and deedes. Yee muſt give an account <hi>of every idle</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 12.</note> 
               <hi>word to God,</hi> and your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences; of every idle word, that hath no <hi>naturall, civill,</hi> or <hi>reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious end:</hi> therefore <hi>Davids</hi> conſcience pleaded againſt him, that he <hi>ſaid in his haſte, all</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 31. 22. Pſal. 116. 11</note> 
               <hi>men are lyars,</hi> even <hi>Samuel</hi> himſelfe in his meſſage from God, and <hi>Peters</hi> conſcience laſhed him to the purpoſe for
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:478:88"/> his deteſtable words in the high-prieſts hall. <hi>Davids</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience alſo comes to his <hi>deeds,</hi> I have ſinned greatly <hi>in that I have done; I have done</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 24. 10.</note> very fooliſhly &amp; <hi>Ezra,</hi> when he preſented others conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as well as his owne, cried out, <hi>and now what ſhall wee ſay?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezr. 9. 10</note> 
               <hi>for wee have forſaken thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dements.</hi> O the large charge of <hi>Conſcience!</hi> As ye muſt hold the light of conſcience, the love of conſcience, and the worke of conſcience; ſo hold the charge of conſcience, that yee may doe as <hi>Paul</hi> would have you, <hi>hold a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Would you now know the grounds of <hi>holding a good</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Why you muſt hold a good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. 1 If it bee gone, God will be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us.</note> 
               <hi>conſcience?</hi> Doe but marke theſe foure that follow. Firſt, if <hi>conſcience</hi> runne away from you, GOD, &amp; your own ſoules will be againſt you. <hi>Gods eyes
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:478:88"/> are purer then to behold iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> with approbation; and when hee with rebukes doth correct man for ſinne, <hi>as a moath hee makes his beauty to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 39. 11</note> 
               <hi>conſume away:</hi> hee doth not preſently thunder out of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, but ſecretly gnawes out the comfort of their hearts, when hee is to <hi>Ephraim as a</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 4. Ier. 20. 3, 4 Pro 28 1 Levit. 26. 37</note> 
               <hi>moath.</hi> He makes them <hi>plagues to themſelves, magor miſſabib, flying when none purſues, at the ſound of a ſhaking leafe,</hi> making every moate a beame, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very beame an whole houſe. Yea, by conſcience he makes them an whole wilderneſſe of woe. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> complained that God would <hi>breake all his</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſ. 38. 13</note> 
               <hi>bones,</hi> that hee could not ſpeak <hi>for anguiſh of ſpirit,</hi> but chatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>like a crane or ſwallow,</hi> and mourned like <hi>a dove Iobs</hi> bitter<note place="margin">Iob. 12. 26</note> things that God wrote againſt him; made him cry out, <hi>that
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:478:89"/> the arrowes</hi> of the Almightie<note place="margin">Iob. 6. 4. 8. Iob. 7. 14. 15.</note> were within him; <hi>ſcared him with dreames and viſions,</hi> and made his ſoule <hi>chooſe ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> and death, rather then life. <hi>Davids</hi> bones <hi>waxed old</hi> with roaring all the day long, <hi>and his moysture was like the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 32. 3. 4.</note> 
               <hi>drought in ſummer,</hi> when <hi>Gods arrowes stucke faſt in him,</hi> tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the power of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Therefore <hi>hold a good conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>nothing will doe</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing will doe us good. Pſal 51.</note> 
               <hi>you good</hi> without a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. Have you all houſes, lands, gold, ſilver, kingdomes, Empires, they will do you no good without this; no <hi>nor faith</hi> it ſelfe: for a <hi>pure heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1. 5</note> and <hi>a good conſcience,</hi> and <hi>faith unfayned</hi> will goe together; they all worke one for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a good conſcience riſeth from a pure heart: and faith unfained cannot bee without
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:478:89"/> a good conſcience. There is a<note place="margin">A foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold ſting in ſinne.</note> fourefold ſting in ſin; the <hi>guilt</hi> of ſin, the <hi>fruits</hi> of ſin, the <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice</hi> of ſin, &amp; the <hi>habits</hi> of ſin. Faith in Chriſt pulls out the two firſt, &amp; a good conſcience from Chriſt the two laſt. If therefore yee would have any good of what you have, hold a good conſcience.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, with a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience<note place="margin">3 With it nothing can doe us hurt.</note> nothing can doe you hurt. It ſtands out againſt all the world. Let ſlanders come, <hi>Paul</hi> ſets the ſentence of his conſcience againſt them, <hi>with me it is a very ſmall thing that I ſhould be judged of you, or of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s Iudgment: for I know nothing by my ſelfe:</hi> &amp; though this juſtifie me not before <hi>God,</hi> yet it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts me againſt your clamors, Let a thouſand troubles come, <hi>Iob</hi> ſets his conſcience againſt<note place="margin">Iob. 31. 35. 36. 37.</note> them all. <hi>Let mine adverſary</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>write a booke againſt
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:478:90"/> me,</hi> I would take it upon my ſhoulder, and binde it as a crown, <hi>and declare my steps,</hi> &amp; goe as a Prince againſt him, yea, a good conſcience ſhal go with you thorough the pikes of death, and the grave. The warfare of our faith, &amp; hope, ſhall end in ſight, and having but our love out of a good conſcience, ſhall paſſe all, and continue for ever.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, a good conſcience<note place="margin">5 It car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries with at more then the whole world. Rom. 2.</note> carries with it more then the whole world to do us good. It carries God along with it. If God go with an ill conſcience <hi>to accuſe,</hi> much more with a good one <hi>to excuſe</hi> &amp; comfort. The ſentence is the judgment of conſcience, but as Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter: &amp; what conſcience ſpeaks (when it is well regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) God confirms, as ye ſee in <hi>Adam</hi> for ill, and in <hi>Iob</hi> for good. It carries all the hoſt of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:478:90"/> heaven and earth along, as Gods great and mighty train. The good conſcience of <hi>Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 6. Dan. 3.</note> is attended with mild lyons; of the three confeſſors, with an unburning fire; of penitent <hi>Ionah,</hi> with a ſanctuary in the<note place="margin">Ioh. 2.</note> helliſh belly of the whale; of <hi>Elijah</hi> with a raven to cook &amp;<note place="margin">1 King. 17 2 Ring. 6.</note> cater for him; and of <hi>Eliſha</hi> with an army of Angels to guard him. And if yours bee not ſo attended, it is with bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; with the immortal ſeed of the word to make you bring forth unto life, and with po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull praier, which landed <hi>Ionah,</hi> quenched the thirſt of<note place="margin">Ion. 2. Iudg. 15. 2 King 19. Ioſh. 10. Ex. 32. 16</note> 
               <hi>Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pſon,</hi> ſlew an hundred four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore and five thouſand ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, ſtopt the courſe of the ſun, and is the wel-pleaſing <hi>bonds</hi> of <hi>God</hi> to hold him cloſe to you for obtaining all good. Therefore hold a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:478:91"/>
            <p>Thus you ſee how you may<note place="margin">Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> hold a good conſcience, &amp; the grounds of it. Oh that I could now dwell in your ſouls, to ſet them on work, totry whether you conforme to this rule of holding a good conſcience, yea or no.</p>
            <p>I finde ſome good people,<note place="margin">Some think they have no good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and why?</note> who (being clouded with temptations) <hi>think they have no conſcience at all,</hi> and therefore that they cannot hold it. They look for more in themſelves <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> then God hath given: They meaſure Gods ſea, not their own buckets: and are therfore unquiet, becauſe they have no more. They ſet patternes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> them too high for them to reach at an inſtant: <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> full ſaile of faith, <hi>Pauls</hi> chariot of conſcience, and thoſe firſt Chriſtians extaſies of joy, <hi>with joy unſpeakeable</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 18.</note> 
               <hi>and glorious even in the fiery tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all:</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:478:91"/> and if they are not thus (though their caſes differ) downe they fall. They reade themſelves ſtill in a lecture of the law, and look for a deal of <hi>legall righteouſnes</hi> to purge co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, before <hi>Iustification</hi> by the bloud of Chriſt, made theirs by faith, to pacifie it: &amp; if they have not, at the <hi>firſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deus et natura non faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt ſaltu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> 
               <hi>leap</hi> what they would, they put off good conſcience, as the high-prieſt <hi>Iudas, what is that to us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I find more wicked people,<note place="margin">So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e think they have all good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, and why?</note> who think they have <hi>all good conſcience.</hi> They ſleepe out the ſtorme, and doe not feele the heart-quake. The God of this world blinds them with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> If he can, they ſhal not <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> faile of profit, pleaſure, or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, while the vines, &amp; olives, and fig-trees are blaſted, the bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bles grow to a full height: therefore their conſciences
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:478:92"/> cannot but be good. They are <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> rock't a ſleepe, and are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake yet, they look not into the perfect law of liberty, and therefore (for want of fight) <hi>covenant with hell and death.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſ. 28.</note> They have leaſure to doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> but <hi>to draw iniquity with cords of vanity, and ſin as it were</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſ. 5.</note> 
               <hi>with cart-ropes:</hi> they ſtill their conſciences with ſweet words, &amp; couzen them with <hi>outward</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 15. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Matth. 7. et 25:</note> 
               <hi>formality.</hi> They are in their owne delights, as in their own proper places: and then as ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> are not heavy when they are where they would be: ſo ſinne troubles not their conſciences while it is in its center. They are <hi>dead in ſinnes</hi>
               <note place="margin">6 ph. 2.</note> 
               <hi>and treſpaſſes;</hi> and if you lay the load of the whole world upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a dead man, he feels it not: ſo, nor conſcience the heavy burthen of ſin. But as a melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholick man, in his paſſionate
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:478:92"/> pleaſures forgets his owne thoughts, but when the game is ended, he thinks more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally, though for the preſent he is ſet up to the merry pinne: ſo the poore ſinner layes aſide his penſiveneſſe to indulge to his preſenr fancy, till the time of rouſing comes. Hence, or from ſuch like ſprings, wicked men thinke they have a good conſcience, and therfore they thinke they<note place="margin">Therefore try whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yee hold good conſcience 1 Try the light of conſcience</note> hold it: therefore it behoves you to try whether you hold a good conſcience, yea or no.</p>
            <p>Do ye hold the light of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience? good ſoules do deſire to enform themſelves in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particle of Gods will for faith and manners, As a good maſter deſires to give light to his ſervants, that they may ſee to work: ſo deale good chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians with conſcience. But do not you love ignorance? In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:478:93"/> ye come to the church, and heare the word, but yee quickly lay it aſide, like a ſtrait payr of ſhoes, wherein he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not go in eaſe. How ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience work (think you) if it have no light? There is an <hi>in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lumen. 1 Innatum. 2 Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</note> 
               <hi>bred</hi> light which will helpe in ſome things; but if ye have not that <hi>ſowed</hi> light which the ſower went out to ſowe by the word of Chriſt, it is not ſo good as it ſhould. <hi>Workes of darkneſſe will bee committed by men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n darkeneſſe, who love not light, becauſe their deedes are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill:</hi> Doe yee therefore hold the light of conſcience?</p>
            <p>Do ye hold the <hi>love of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience?</hi> you will all ſay, yes: &amp;<note place="margin">2 Try the love of conſcience</note> I grant that ye love it as a dog loves a cudgel. It is ready to ſmite you at every turne, as it can ſpy day at a little hole, and <hi>to make your hearts heavy in the midſt of laughter,</hi> and doe you
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:478:93"/> love this? A good mans loves it dearly. Oh ſaith he, let mee have a good conſcience ſtil! let a righteous conſcience ſmite mee ſtil: let it bee my counſellour, comforter, corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor ſtil. But had you not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be without it? yee cannot gaine ſo much as you would for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience: ye cannot drink ſo freely of pleaſure as you would for conſcience: ye can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not advance your ſelves as you would for conſcience, Oh how it troubles you! therefore ye wound it, ſmother it, ſtop the mouth of it, and will not heare it, though a good man might by it <hi>bee ſatisfied from</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 14, 14.</note> 
               <hi>himſelfe,</hi> Is this to hold the love of conſcience?</p>
            <p>Do ye hold <hi>the worke of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience?</hi>
               <note place="margin">3 Try the worke of conſcience Eſ 57.</note> A good man will let it perfect its work in the feare of God. He propounds fairly; he that <hi>is broken hearted ſhall bee
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:478:94"/> comforted:</hi> he that is weary and preſſed down with ſinnes ſhal<note place="margin">Math. 11. Apoc. 2.</note> be refreſhed: he that fights the good fight of faith, ſhall have the crown of life: he that adds to his faith knowledge, to his knowledge vertue, &amp; ſo forth, <hi>ſhall make his calling and electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.</note> 
               <hi>ſure,</hi> becauſe he ſhal neither be barren nor unfruitfull: hee that hath the fruits of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,<note place="margin">Gal. 5. 22. 23.</note> againſt him there is no law to condemne. Hee applies as truely: but I have a broken heart, I am weary of ſin, I fight faithfully according to ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth received, I chaine my graces together in act (as occaſion is offered) as I have them in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, and as I have the fruits of the ſpirit in me: therefore hee concludes as neceſſarily, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo long as I continue in this eſtate, I ſhal have comfort heere, and ſalvation hereafter. A wicked man wil ſometimes
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:478:94"/> ſuffer conſcience to work too, according to light: <hi>Abimelechs</hi> conſcience will not let him wrong <hi>Abrahams</hi> wife, which<note place="margin">Gen. 20.</note> comes not becauſe the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is <hi>good out of faith</hi> unfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but <hi>good out of feare and awe.</hi> But tell me: doe yee ſuffer conſcience to worke in all things? Then would yee ſo powerfully conclude againſt your ſelves, that yee muſt ſay,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 9. 10.</note> I muſt amend, or periſh. <hi>No unrighteous perſon</hi> what ever, whether <hi>fornicator, adulterer, reviler, drunkard, covetous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, extortioner,</hi> ſhal inherit the kingdome of heaven: but I am ſo, and ſo; therefore <hi>in this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate,</hi> I ſhall never get heaven. Hee that neglects the call of God, ſhal call upon God, and God will not heare, but laugh<note place="margin">Pro. 1.</note> when his deſtruction comes: but I have done ſo; therefore God will deale ſo with mee.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:478:95"/> 
               <hi>Hee that being often reproved,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 29 1.</note> 
               <hi>hardneth his necke, ſhall ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly be deſtroyed without reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy:</hi> but I have hardened my necke againſt all reproofes; therfore what may I look for (if I amend not) but deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Doe ye thus conclude for your amendment? Doe ye not rather conclude quite other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe? Gods word ſaith ſo, &amp; ſo; but I do not ſo do; or if I do otherwiſe, God will ſave ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and I ſhall eſcape. Is this to hold the worke of coſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, doe yee hold the<note place="margin">4 Try the charge of conſcience.</note> charge of conſcience? What an univerſal biſhopricke hath conſcience over the whole man, and all of man? There is no inclination, imagination, power, thought, word, or deed, but it is under the power of conſcience, and do ye hold this? <hi>Davids</hi> conſcience loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:478:95"/> to his inclinations; I was<note place="margin">Pſal. 18. 23</note> upright before God, and kept my ſelfe <hi>from my wickedneſſe. Agurs</hi> conſcience looked to his underſtanding &amp; thoughts; if thou haſt done fooliſhly, <hi>if</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 30. 21</note> 
               <hi>thou have thought evill,</hi> lay thy hand upon thy mouth. <hi>Davids</hi> conſcience looked to his words; I will <hi>keepe my mouth</hi> with a bridle: and to his deeds,<note place="margin">Pſal 39.</note> I ſaid <hi>I will take heede unto my waies.</hi> But as Chriſt did mourn within himſelfe, when he ſaw the multitude, becauſe they were <hi>as ſheepe without a ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 9. 36.</note> ſo may you for the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of conſcience in all theſe. Yee are inclined to every evil way, yet conſcience takes no notice. How is your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding overwhelmed with ignorance, and ſtuffed with worldly vanity? How are your memories charged with unprofitables, and your affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:478:96"/> laviſhed wickedly, and yet conſcience is ſilent? your thoughts, words, and deedes, are not viſited by conſcience as they ſhould. It neither viewes, nor cenſures, nor cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects, as is meete. Oh why doe you not hold conſcience? Let it looke to every ſecret, and when it knows the duty, let it looke about and apply it (as need is) to every part &amp; power of body and ſoule. This will work amendment for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and care for the time to come, and ſo ſhall yee hold conſcience.</p>
            <p>It may be you will ſay, how<note place="margin">How to help to the holding of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> ſhall I helpe my ſelfe forward to ſuch a glorious work? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, Get a <hi>a rich mine of grace and duty</hi> into your hearts. As a <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> good man hath a good trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in his heart: ſo muſt you, by laying up the word <hi>in your</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 16. Pro. 6.</note> 
               <hi>hearts,</hi> and <hi>binding</hi> it to your
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:478:96"/> 
               <hi>hearts,</hi> by a powerful impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>Preſent</hi> this treaſure to your conſciences, that it may make you <hi>ſmite your ſelves upon your thighes,</hi> and ſay, <hi>what have I done?</hi> Then <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>walke in the preſence of God,</hi> as <hi>David, when I awake, I</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 139.</note> 
               <hi>am ever before thee:</hi> and then the ſervant will worke when hee is before his maſter. Next, have a ſetled <hi>watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> over all your wayes, covenanting with heart, eyes, tongue, and hand, not wilfully to ſinne againſt God.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, <hi>commit your</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
               <hi>waeyes</hi> to GOD by hearty prayers, and hee will rectifie all by the bloud and ſpirit of your JESVS: and ſo, ſurely, ſhall <hi>you hold both faith, and a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> too, to the comfort of your ſoules, and to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:478:97"/> the Glory of your GOD, to whom bee praiſe, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and Glory now, and for ever,</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Sept. 1. 1638.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Tho. Wykes.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:478:97"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
